本字幕由志愿者义务贡献，采用许可协议
知识共享 署名-非商业性使用-相同方式共享 3.0 美国
Stanford University.
斯坦福大学
>> Welcome to Stanford CS193p, Developing Applications for
欢迎参加 2017 年冬季学期斯坦福
iOS, this is Winter quarter 2017.
CS193P 课程，iOS 应用程序开发
Today we are going to talk about a few things.
今天我们将讨论几个东西
We're gonna start though giving a demo about what I
我们将通过展示一个上节课谈论过的
talked about last time which is multiple MVCs.
关于多个 MVC 的 demo 来开始
After that I'm gonna do some slides on the view controller
在那之后我将展示几个关于视图控制器生命周期的
lifecycle, really important mechanism for finding out
幻灯片，一个非常重要的关于 MVC 随着
what's going on with your MVC as time goes flows by.
时间的流逝都会发生些什么的机制
And if I have time left at the end, I'm gonna start
如果最后有时间的话，我将讲一些
talking a little bit about memory management,
关于内存管理的一点东西
which is basically managing the memory of reference types,
也就是管理引用类型（储存在堆里的东西）
things that are in the heap.
的内存的方法
How do they get managed?
它们如何被管理？
How do they know when the stay in the heap, or
它们如何知道什么时候该待在堆里，或者
leave the heap?
离开堆？
But first, we're gonna start with this demo.
但是首先，我们将从这个 demo 开始
I'm calling this demo emotions in FaceIt.
我给这个 demo 取名叫 Emotions in FaceIt
If you remember last time,
如果你还记得的话
we built a nice MVC that knows how to draw a face.
之前我们创建了一个不错的知道如何绘制一张脸的 MVC
It was a pretty generic MVC and
这个 MVC 非常典型并且
had a model, which is a facial expression.
还有一个模型，也就是面部表情
So now we're gonna build a more complicated app that has
那么现在我们要创建一个更复杂的
two MVCs.
拥有两个 MVC 的 app
One MVCs is going to let you choose an emotion.
一个 MVC 是让你选择一个心情
Like happy or sad.
像是开心或者伤心
And then the other MVC is just gonna be our generic face
然后另一个 MVC 就是我们的脸的视图
view, and it's gonna show that emotion.
用来表现那个心情
By doing that, we're gonna learn
我们会通过使用那个学着
how to use the split view controller and
如何使用分屏控制器
navigation controller, combine MVCs, to make a bigger app
导航控制器，来包含所有的 MVC，以创建更复杂的程序
It's a simple example because of time constraints but
由于时间的限制，这会是一个简单一点的例子，但是
you should get the idea.
你应该要懂实现的方法
So here I'm back in FaceIt, this demo we had last time.
那么现在我回到了那个 FaceIt，之前的那个 demo
One thing before I start,
在我开始前有一件事
I wanted to show you something you're going to need for
我想展示给你们一些家庭作业中会需要的东西
your homework, which is how to rename a ViewController.
也就是如何重命名一个 ViewController
I have this ViewController here.
我这里有个 ViewController
This is the ViewController that shows the face.
这就是用来展现那个脸的 ViewController
Remember, here's the faceView var and here's it's model.
记住了，这个是变量 faceView 然后这是 ViewController 的模型
So I don't like this name ViewController.
所以我不喜欢这个名字 ViewController
It's really quite too generic.
这太普通了
It's almost like it's super class,
几乎都跟它的父类一样了
which is UIViewController.
也就是 UIViewController
Really this wants to be some specifically named
这应该是一个特殊名字的 ViewController
view controller, and in this case it shows a face so
在这一个情况下它展示了一个脸
this probably best called it faceviewcontroller.
所以大概最好的名字就是 FaceViewController 了
So I wanna just type face right here, and
那么我就在这里输入 Face 然后
hope that's enough.
希望这样就足够了
But of course as I mentioned in like lecture number one
但是当然了就像我在第一节课中提到过的
that's not enough.
这还不够
You can't just rename right there.
你不能仅仅就在那里重命名
You actually have to rename a couple of other things.
事实上你还需要重命名一些别的东西
One, the file that it's in, you see the file,
第一个，它所在的文件，看这个文件
is still called viewcontroller.swift.
仍然叫做 ViewController.swift
We almost always want to have our name of
我们通常希望文件的名字跟
our file be the same as the primary class that's in there.
里面的主类的名字一样
Now, it's not required in swift, the name of the file
但是在 Swift 中没有要求，文件名字可以
could be completely different than any class in there.
跟内部的任何一个类名完全不一样
But generally,
但是通常情况下
to kinda help people find the code that they're looking for,
为了帮助人们找到他们需要的代码
we wanna have the name of the file pretty much match
我们希望给文件取名为
the name of the main class.
主类的名字
It could be multiple classes in a Swift file,
在一个小小的文件中可以有很多类
that's perfectly allowed as well, but
这当然可以，但是
if the main one.
只需要主类名字就可以
You might think, well that's enough, but
你可能会想，这就够了吧，但是
there's one more very,
在 storyboard 中还有一个非常
very important piece of this which is in the story board.
非常重要的一个东西
We haven't really talked too much about this- well
我们还没谈过它很多
actually, we did see it, with the Face View.
不过事实上我们看到过它，就在 faceView 里
We did this with Face View, but
在 faceView 里我们实现过它，但是
we need to inspect this controller, and I'm
我们需要检查这个控制器
gonna click on the controller by clicking this orange thing
我将通过点击这个上面橘色的东西来选择这一整个控制器
up here, that represents the controller for this whole MVC.
也就是整一个 MVC 的控制器
And I'm gonna go over to this same inspector we went on when we
然后我来到这个跟之前把
changed the face view from being a generic UI view to
faceView 从普通的 UIView 变换到
being a specific face view.
一个特殊的 FaceView 一样的检查器中
'm gonna do the exact same thing here.
我这里会做一模一样的事
So 'm picking this whole view controller and
那么我全选了这个控制器然后
'm going to the identity inspector up here and
来到这上面的这个 Identity Inspector，接下来
'm gonna change the class from ViewController,
把这个 class 从 ViewController
that's what it was the generic name to Face view controller.
也就是通用名字到 FaceViewController
So if you forget to do this piece,
所以如果你忘记做这个的话
than none of your outlets are gonna be hooked up.
那么你的所有出口（@IBOutlet）都不会被连接
And iOS is gonna be very confused because you're
然后 iOS 就会很疑惑因为
gonna be asking it to couple outlets to a different class.
你要求它把这些出口连接到另一个不同的类
SomeClasses doesn't exist anymore cuz I renamed it away.
由于我重命名了，有些类也就不存在了
You'll need to do that for your homework.
你们的家庭作业里将用到
You'll have to change your current calculator
你要把你们目前的计算器
MVC from being called View Controller
MVC 从 ViewController 改变到
to being called something like Calculator View Controller and
叫做 CalculatorViewController
that's because you're gonna have this new MVC- the graph
这是因为你将有这个新的 MVC 也就是图像视图控制器
view controller- and you wanna make clear which one is which.
并且你想明确哪一个是哪一个
Now I'm not gonna touch my Face View Controller or
从现在开始，这个 demo 中，我一点都不会去碰 FaceViewController
MVC at all in this demo from here on.
或者 MVC
I'm gonna build this multi-MVC app, and
我会创建这个多个 MVC 的 app，并且
I'm gonna use the face view controller that I just
我将使用之前完成的 FaceViewController
finished building last time as a reusable component.
把它作为可重用的组件
Just like your graph view
就像你们家庭作业中
controller is gonna be a reusable MVC in your homework.
你们的图形视图控制器会是一个可重用的 MVC 一样
I said that I wanted to have two MVCs.
我说过了我想要两个 MVC
One is just a list of some emotions.
一个是一系列的心情
And then I'm going to use this MVC to show that emotion.
然后我将用这个 MVC 来展现那些心情
So let's just dive right into this and
那么就让我们深入它并且
put another MVC into our storyboard.
把另一个 MVC 放进我们的 storyboard 中吧
We have this one MVC, we get another one, in exactly
我们现在有了这个 MVC，然后我们通过
the same way that we get a new button or something like that,
跟新添加一个按钮或者之类的一样来得到另一个 MVC
which is to go down here to the utilities window
也就是在这下面的辅助工具窗口
at the bottom here and just drag out a view controller.
拖出一个视图控制器
You just pull it out and
只要把它拉出来，然后
drag it right into your storyboard like that.
像这样拖放到你的 storyboard 就可以了
Now this MVC right here,
那么这里的这个 MVC
what's gonna be its class of it's controller?
它的控制器会是哪个类呢？
It's just going to be (if we select it by clicking on
如果我们点击这个橘色的东西的话
the orange thing), UI view controller.
就能看到，是一个 UIViewController
In other words not a sub class.
也就是不是一个子类
So we're gonna need to create a custom sub class for
那么我们就需要为这个视图控制器创建一个
this view controller just like we have for
自定义的子类
our face view controller.
就像我们的 FaceViewController 一样
We'll do that in a second.
我们马上就会这么做
Before we do that though,
但在这之前
I wanna talk about this little arrow.
我想谈一谈这个小箭头
You see this arrow right here?
你们看到这里的这个小箭头了吗
This is the arrow that tells iOS when this app launches,
这是一个告诉 iOS 当 app 启动时
use this MVC as the first thing that appears.
用这个 MVC 作为第一个显示的东西的箭头
It's like the "entry" into the storyboard.
就像是进入 storyboard 的入口
And so if I want it to be the other one,
那么如果我想让它换一个的话
I can just pick it up with the mouse.
我可以用鼠标选择它
And drop it on that one.
然后把它放到另一个 MVC 上
And now this one is my entry MVC.
那么现在这个就是我的初始 MVC 了
I also want you to notice that we have a warning here.
我还想让你们注意到这里有一个警告
You see this yellow warning?
你看到这个黄色的警告了吗
I'm gonna click on that,
我将点击它
and we'll see here it says face view controller is
然后我们就将看到它说 FaceViewController 是
unreachable, because it has no entry points.
不可达的，因为它没有入口
It's saying this view controller right here with
意思是这个有一张脸的视图控制器
the face, you're never gonna see that in your app.
你在 app 中将永远看不到它
Which is true, because my app is gonna come in here to this
这是对的，因为我的 app 会进入这个
blank one and I can't get to the FaceView from there.
空白的 MVC，并且我不能进入那个 FaceView
Now of course we're going to add SplitView controller,
当然现在我们要添加分屏控制器
and navigation controllers, and we're eventually gonna be
和导航控制器，然后终究
able to get there, but I just want you to understand what
能到达那里，但是我只是想让你们能苟理解
this unsupported configuration means.
这个不支持的标记意味着什么
It just means that you can't get there.
这意思就是你到达不了那里
If I move this back, this arrow off of this and
如果我把它移回去，把这个箭头移回到这里
back over to here, now this one, you see,
那么这个，看
view controller is unreachable.
这个 ViewController 就不可达了
Which makes perfect sense.
就是这个道理
If I run this app by the way, let's go ahead and run, you're
如果我运行这个 app 的话，你就将看到
gonna see that my app's gonna come up completely blank.
这个 app 会出现完全的一片空白
That face will not be there because that MVC is
这个脸表情不会在那里，因为那个 MVC
really not even being used.
甚至都没被使用到
It's in the storyboard right now, but
它存在于 storyboard，但是
since it's not accessible we can't navigate to it.
由于它不可达，我们不能导航到它
We can't segue to it (to use the terminology you
我们不能 segue 到它
learned last time).
segue，上节课讲的转场的专业术语
We get this completely blank UI.
我们只会得到这个完全空白的 UI 界面
If we want to have things like outlets and actions,
如果我们想在这个控制器上加些出口和方法（@IBAction）
or anything like that, with this View Controller, it needs
或者其他诸如此类的话，它就需要
to have a custom subclass of UI view controller,
有一个继承 UIViewController 的自定义子类
it can't just be generic.
它不能是普通型的
So we're gonna create that.
那么我们将创建那个
We're gonna go to File, New File, remember that's always
选择 File，然后 New，记住每次要创建一个新的 UIView 的子类的时候
where we go when we create a new UI View Subclass,
一个新的 UIViewController，任意的像是 Calculator Brain那样的
a new UI View Controller, any Calculator brain.
我们都是这么操作的
We did all those from new file.
我们都是从 New File 开始的
So I'm gonna click new file.
所以我要点 New File 了
This is gonna be a sub class of an iOS class, UIViewController.
这将是 iOS 系统类，UIViewController 的子类
I'm gonna pick this one here, cocoa touch class.
我这里要选这个，Cocoa Touch Class
We use swift file over here when it was just
当时我们用这里的 Swift 文件来创建
calculator brain, not a sub class of anything.
当时那个 CalculatorBrain，不是任何的子类，就只是 Swift 文件
But here, we're gonna do cocoa touch class.
但是这里，我们只需要 Cocoa Touch Class
And it says subclass of what?
然后它说这是谁的子类呢？
Okay, it's even defaulted here to UIVewController.
默认的是 UIViewController 的子类
Remember earlier we picked UIView.
记得先前我们选择 UIView 时
We're gonna leave this UIViewController and I'm gonna
放着这个 UIViewController 然后
call this view controller my EmotionsViewController.
我要给这个 ViewController 取名叫做 EmotionsViewController
So this gonna show the emotions like happy,
所以这个就是用来显示心情的，例如开心
sad, whatever, and
伤心，之类的
then I'm gonna click on it to go show the face.
然后我只要点击后就能展现对应的脸的图像
So I just do that.
接着点击 Next
Go over here, it says where do you wanna put it.
来到了这里，Xcode 询问你想要把这个文件放在哪里
Again, I do not wanna put it here.
再一次的，我不想把它放在这里
You see where it says Group FaceIt, and
你们看这个叫做 FaceIt 的包，然后
it has that blue icon.
它有一个蓝色的图标
We wanna put it down in here.
我们要把它放在这下面的文件夹里
So if you put it here,
如果你放在这里的话
it's gonna be at the very top level.
文件就会在最顶级
Down here, it's with all your other classes space
放在下面一个文件夹里的话，它就会和你别的一些类在一起
faceview.swift, etc.
FaceView.swift 之类的
So make sure you remember to do that.
所以要保证你们记得做这个
So here I popped it in there.
那么现在我把它放在了那里
There's my view controller selected in the navigator.
在导航器中选定的是我的视图控制器
Let's make the navigator a little bit wider, so
让我们把导航器拉宽一点，那么
you can read it, there we go.
你就能看得到名字了
EmotionsViewController and
也就是 EmotionViewController 并且
you can see it's giving me a little bit of code.
你能看到它提供了一些代码
These right here are part of the ViewController life cycle,
选定的这些是视图控制器的生命周期的一部分
which I promise I'm gonna talk about right after this
也就是我承诺过这之后会讲的东西
but not now.
但不是现在
There's this other thing that's commented out down
还有一些被注释掉的其他东西在这里
here, which is actually really important to today's lecture.
也就是今天课程中很重要的东西
This is Navigation method,
这是导航方法
which you know all too well from last lecture.
也就是你们上节课学到很多的那个
It's called prepare for segue.
它叫做 prepare(for segue:)
This is the method that's gonna be used when we segue or
这就是当我们从一个 MVC 转换
transition from this MVC to another one.
或 segue 到另一个 MVC 时用到的方法
And we have to prepare that other one to do its job and
然后我们必须让另一个 MVC 准备做它的工作
here's why we do it, prepare for segue.
这就是我们为什么需要这个 prepare(for segue:) 了
We'll be coming back and implementing prepare for
我们马上会回到这里并且
segue, in just a minute.
实现这个 prepare(for segue:)，但是要等下
Now that we have this new class, EmotionsViewController,
现在我们有了这个新的类叫做 EmotionsViewController
we have to do the exact same thing we just did.
我们必须做跟之前做过的完全一样的事情
Which is to go back to our storyboard,
也就是回到我们的 storyboard 中
click on this View controller, go to the Utilities window,
点击这个视图控制器，来到工具栏窗口
get that identity inspector up.
选择上面的这个 Identity Inspector
And then pick the class EmotionsViewController, so
然后在 Class 中选择 EmotionsViewController ，那么
that this is now an EmotionsViewController,
这个现在就是一个 EmotionsViewController 的类了
not a generic UIView controller.
不是一个普通的 UIViewController
So now that we've hooked that up,
那么现在我们已经连接好了
we can start building our UI here.
可以开始创建我们的 UI 界面了
What is our UI here?
这里的 UI 界面会是怎样的呢？
It's gonna be super simple,
它将非常简单
I'm just gonna grab some buttons, so
我只要拉取一些按钮
let's get one here,
那么让我们拿一个吧
let's change some attributes of that button.
然后改变些那个按钮的属性
How about let's make the font really big,
不如让我们把它的字体变得非常大吧
something like 40 point is probably good.
例如 40 可能会不错
Let's go ahead and make some more of them,
然后继续，制作些更多的按钮
I'm gonna copy and paste.
我就复制粘贴吧
I think three of them is enough for this demo.
我认为三个按钮对这个 demo 来说就足够了
We'll have one of our emotions be sad, another emotion be
我们将其中一个心情设置为 Sad ，另一个
happy and I don't know if this is an emotion but
设置为 Happy ，然后说实话我也不知道这算不算心情但是
we'll have this one be worried.
还是把剩下的这个设置为 Worried
Those are gonna be our three things we're gonna show
那就是三个我们将用我们的 FaceView
with our face.
来展现的东西了
So I'm gonna select them all and stack them up in a stack
然后我全选它们，然后用一个 Stack View 来
view, let's put a little space in between them there.
把它们堆起来，让我们给它们之间腾点空间
We'll fill equally even though they're all buttons, so
即使它们都是按钮，仍然选择 Fill Equally 那么
they're all gonna be filled equally anyway.
它们无论何种情况都会被平均地填充
So we've got this nice stack view right here.
那么现在我们得到了一个不错的 Stack View 了
Now, one thing about this stack view is, if I put it
现在，有一个关于这个 Stack View 的问题是，如果我把它
here and I go down to look at my various orientations and
放在这里然后看我的多设备选项里
devices, if I go landscape here, "Ugh!".
如果选择这里的横屏模式的话，噢天呐
It gets cut off, right?
它被截断了，对不？
So I really want these, this stack to stay in the middle.
所以我很需要这个堆保持在屏幕中间
I don't wanna do the same thing I did with
我不想做之前在 Calculator demo 中把
the calculator where I'm sticking it to the edges.
它们连接到边线上那样的事
I just want it to stay in the middle cuz I don't want
我只是想让它待在中间因为我不想
the buttons to be kinda really spread out.
让这些按钮拉伸之类的
I want them to stay kind of collected but
我想让它们保持不变但是
I want them in the middle.
想让它们在中间
I can still do that with the autolayout,
我仍然可以用自动布局来完成
the same way we did in the last demo.
也就是上一个 demo 中一样的方法
I'm just gonna pick up the thing and
我只要选定它然后
use the blue lines to indicate what I want.
用蓝线来指示我想要的
Which is I want this in the center.
也就是把它放在正中间
I'm holding this, so
我拿着它
that the blue lines come on in the center.
这些蓝线标识了中间
And when I let go, iOS interface builder here knows "
然后当我放开它，Interface Builder 就知道了
he wants that in the center".
“噢，他想让那个处于中心位置”
So that when I go down here to this little guy again and
那么当我再次来到下面这个小按钮并且
I say reset to suggested constraints,
选择了这个 Reset to Suggested Constraints
just like I did in the last lecture,
就像我上节课做的那样
it creates constraints that put it in the middle.
它创建了对应的约束然后把它放到中间
And we can verify that by going up to this inspector,
并且我们可以通过核对这个检查器
this is the size inspector.
这是尺寸检查器
It shows the size of the thing but
它展示了事物的尺寸但是
it also shows the constraints, the autolayout constraints.
它也能展示约束，那些自动布局的约束
And this is constrained to align its center horizontally
约束使它的中心
to the superview center and
水平居中于父视图的中心
it's centered vertically to the superview center.
并且竖直居中于它的父视图的中心
Now if we do the rotation,
那么现在如果我们旋转的话
we see that it stays in the center.
我们能看到它仍旧保持在中心
I'm giving you a little taste of autolayout,
目前我让你们尝了一点点自动布局的味道
I'm gonna give a whole lecture on autolayout
在几个星期里
in a couple weeks.
我会给你们上一个专门关于自动布局的课
But I'm just trying to give you a little hint
但现在我只是试着给你们一些
about how it works for now.
它如何工作的提示
Alright, so we have this, this is our UI,
好的，那么我们现在有了这个 UI 界面
that's the entire UI that we're gonna do.
这就是我们要完成的全部 UI 了
Now let's go ahead and run this,
那么继续，我们运行一下
run it on iPhone briefly here
简要地在 iPhone 模拟器上运行下
Just to make sure that we've actually put this in our UI.
只是为了确认我们已经把这些放到我们的 UI 界面上了
There it is. Sure enough if I click on it,
这就是了。能够点击
rotation, seems to work fine.
旋转的话，看起来也可以
We can even check to see, does this work on iPad?
我们甚至可以确认下如果在 iPad 上的话能否成功？
Let's try this one now right there.
试试看那个选项
Here it is, here's our UI.
这就是了，这个就是我们的 UI 界面
It's working fine here and we can rotate here as well and
看起来不错，然后我们也可以旋转屏幕
get this gigantic landscape iPad.
然后得到了这个巨大的横屏模式的 iPad
Is there any way to go smaller?
有什么方法能变小吗？
What's the smallest we can go scale?
我们最小能缩放到多少？
25%?
25%？
There we go, that's small enough.
不错，足够小了
So we've got all this screen real estate here on an iPad.
那么我们现在在一个 iPad 上得到了这个屏幕
It's be really great to use the split view to have these
如果用分屏的话效果会很好
words on the left and the face that matches it on the right.
也就是在左边有这些字，然后右边是对应的脸的效果
So that's exactly what we're gonna do,
所以这就是我们要做的事情
we're gonna go back to our storyboard right here and
我们将回到我们的 storyboard
make that happen.
然后实现它
And to do that, again, is just a matter of dragging something
为了完成这个功能，再一次的，就只是拖拉一些东西的事情
out, I'm gonna make my scale really small here, so
我会缩放得小一些
you can see this as we drag it out.
在这里拉动就可以
But here we're gonna drag out the split view controller
但是这里我们将拖出一个分屏控制器
cuz we wanna put these two MVCs in an MVC
因为我们想把这两个 MVC 放到一个 MVC 里
that has them as part of its view.
也就是把这两个 MVC 作为它自身视图的 MVC
So when I drag this out, you're actually
所以当我把这个拖拉出来的时候，事实上你能看到
gonna see I get more than just a split view,
我得到了不止一个分屏
I get some other little MVCs that come along with it here.
我还得到了一些随之而来的小的 MVC
And I don't really need any of these other
并且我并不是真的需要这些
MVCs that come along with it.
伴随而来的 MVC
Trying to make your life easier, but
试着让它变简单些，但是我也
I find that 99% of the time,
发现99%的概率上
you don't need these other things that come with it.
你不需要这些伴随而来的东西
So I'm just going here and select those and delete them.
那么我就来到这里，选择它们，然后删除它们
So let's get rid of this one.
让我们摆脱这一个 MVC
Whoops! Not the whole thing.
噢糟糕！不是所有的事物
Let's just get rid of this one,
只要摆脱这一个
sorry, there and we're gonna get rid of this one and
然后再摆脱这个和
we get rid of that one.
那一个
I'm just left with my split view controller and,
我只要留下我的分屏控制器然后
of course, my two MVCs are here.
当然了，我的两个 MVC 在这里
Let's move this little more over to the side here,
让我们把这个往边上移一些
scroll down a bit.
然后往下放一点
And now I just wanna make this be the master of my split view
然后现在我要这一个 MVC 成为分屏控制器里的主视图
controller and I want this to be my detail.
然后这一个是细节视图
Whoops, other way around,
噢，换一下
this is the master, this is the detail.
这是主视图，这是细节视图
When the app starts, I don't want it to start here,
当运行 app 时，我不想让它从这开始
I want it to start here, don't forget this step.
我想让它从这里开始，不要忘记这一步
If you want the app to come here and
如果你想要这个 app 能运行并且
then show the split view controller with both things.
展示包含两个 MVC 的分屏控制器的话
So how do I make this the master and this the detail?
那么我如何让这个变成主视图并且让这一个变成细节视图呢
I'm just gonna hold down control and
我只要按住 control 键并且
drag from the split view controller to the master.
从分屏控制器拖拉到主视图
And then in here,
然后在这里
Only these two, master and detail.
只要选这两个，主视图和细节视图
So I'm gonna make that one the master,
那么我要让那个成为主视图
it makes this little master connection there,
它就在那里创建了一个小小的主视图连接
that's not a segue by the way, that's a kind of like,
顺带一提，这不是 segue，这是一种
somewhat like an outlet connection but
像是出口连接，但是
it's a specific connection to that master var there.
是一种到那个 master 变量的特殊连接
This one is the detail.
这一个是细节视图
So I've made my master and my detail here.
那么我已经完成了主视图和细节视图了
Zoom in a little bit.
稍微放大一点
That's really all I need to do to get these both on screen.
这就是想要让这两个都出现在屏幕上需要做的事情
So let's go ahead and run and see what happens here.
那么继续，我们运行一下来看看如何
Alright, so here we go.
好吧，那么开始
Sure enough, there's the face on the right.
当然，右边有这个脸图
Here's this stuff on the left.
左边有这些东西
And if I click this, nothing happens.
并且如果我点击，不会发生什么
The face doesn't show.
对应的脸不会展现出来
Now why does nothing happen there?
那么为什么什么都不会发生呢？
Because we have to do the step of having a segue.
因为我们必须完成创建一个 segue 的步骤
If we want to move to a different MVC,
如果我们想转到另一个不同的 MVC
we have to segue to it.
我们必须 segue 到它
Each of these is gonna have to have the segue to this MVC.
这三个选项中每一个都需要连到这个 MVC 的 segue
And when it segues, it's gonna replace that MVC with a new
并且当它 segue 的时候，它将用一个
one that's properly prepared to show that motion.
显示准备好新表情的 MVC 来替换原来的 MVC
Let's go do our segues.
让我们开始完成我们的 segue 吧
Segues also of course,
当然了，segue 也是通过
we use our favorite gesture which is Ctrl + drag.
使用我们最喜欢的快捷键也就是 control + 拖拉
So if I wanna make a sad segue, I'm just gonna hold
那么如果我想要创建一个 sad segue 的话，我只要按住
down Ctrl and drag it to the MVC that I want to segue to,
control 键然后把它连到想要 segue 到的 MVC
the MVC I want to show when I press Sad.
当我按 sad 键时想要显示的 MVC
So I do that.
那么我这么做好了
Now, you notice that I have some choices of what
现在，你注意到有一些选项
kind of presentation, what kind of segue I want.
我想要什么种类的转场，什么种类的 segue
For example, Present As Popover would present
例如，Present As Popover 选项将会
the thing I'm segueing to in a little popover window on
把正在 segue 的东西展示在一个小的在最顶级的
top of everything else.
弹窗中
Present Modally would take over the whole screen and
Present Modally 将占满整个屏幕然后
show the new MVC.
展示这个新的 MVC
Then there's show and show detail.
然后就是 Show 和 Show Detail
Show is only used when you're in a navigation controller,
Show 选项只会在一个导航控制器中用到
the thing where they've got the cards sliding on top,
也就是会把卡片排到顶部的那一个控制器
like the settings example I showed you.
就像之前展示给你们看过的那个设置
Show detail is used in a split view setting or in a hybrid
Show detail 是用于一个分屏控制器或者一个
setting, where sometimes you're in a split view, and
混合设置的，也就是有时你在分屏视图，有时
sometimes you're in navigation view,
你在导航视图
which is gonna be the case that we're gonna be in here.
也就是我们这里会碰到的情况
Show detail means show this in the detail side of
Show detail 意味着会把这个展示在分屏视图
the split view.
里的细节控制器那一边
I'm gonna show detail there.
我将在那里展示细节控制器
I've made this segue, you see it appeared right here.
我已经创建了这个 segue，看到出现在这里的东西了没
This is a segue,
这是一个 segue
looks a little different from this thing,
看起来跟这个有点不大一样
a little different icon right there.
图标有些不同
This is a segue and you can click on it, and
这是一个 segue 并且你可以点击它，而且
in fact you can even inspect it.
事实上你甚至可以检查它
And you must inspect it, in fact,
事实上你必须检查它
go to the attributes inspector and inspect it, because you're
来到 Attribute Inspector 并且检查它，因为
always gonna wanna give every segue an identifier.
通常来说你都要给每一个 segue 一个标识符
This is just a unique string, that in your code you'll
就是一个独一无二的字符串，在代码中
be able to reference in order to say,
通过引用名字来实现
"I'm talking about this segue right here".
“我说的是这个 segue”
So, I'm gonna call this my sad segue.
那么我要给这个 segue 取名为 sad
Then I'm gonna do the exact same thing here for happy.
然后我将对 Happy 做同样的事
I'm gonna just show detail on that one.
连接细节控制器
I'm gonna inspect that segue.
检查那个 segue
See, there's our sad one.
看到没，那个是我们的 sad segue
Notice that when you pick a segue,
注意当你选择一个 segue 时
it shows you what it's segueing from.
它会展示给你它从哪里 segue 来的
If I pick this one, it shows it seguing from the other one,
如果我选择这个，它就展示它是从另一个按钮 segue 来的
so we know which one it is.
那么我们就能知道这是哪一个的 segue 了
So this is the happy one, and
那么这是 happy，然后
then we'll have our little worried segue.
我们将创建我们的 worried segue
Where's that one?
那个在哪呢？
It's right there, worried.
在那呢，然后取名 worried
Okay, so that's it.
这就是全部了
So we've created these segues, put them in the, we'll put it
我们已经创建了这些 segue，首先把它们放在
into split view first, then we created the segues.
分屏控制器里，然后创建 segue
And now when you click on those buttons,
那么现在当你点击这些按钮时
it's going to segue to this detail and in fact in a split
它就会 segue 到这个细节控制器里。事实上
view it replaces the one that's there with a new one.
在分屏控制器里会用一个新的 MVC 替换掉之前的 MVC
Remember that segues always create a new one,
记住，segue 总是都会创建一个新的 MVC
Don't forget that, that segues always create a new one.
不要忘记
Something easy to forget.
这很容易被忽略
Especially in the split view, it looks like,
特别是在分屏控制器里，它看起来就像
" it just changed the one that was already there".
“它仅仅只是改变了原本存在于那里的 MVC”
But no, it actually just completely replaced that
但是不是的，事实上它是通过 segue 完完全全地替换了
detail segue by doing that.
原本的细节控制器 MVC
If we run this it it's gonna look like
如果现在我们运行的话它会看起来像是
it doesn't didn't even work.
没有效果
Even though we hooked these segues up,
即使我们已经把这些连接了起来
it looks like it's just not doing anything, watch.
但是它看起来仍然像是什么都没做
Okay, so is he sad, happy, worried, nothing is happening.
好，Sad，Happy，Worried，什么都没改变
Absolutely nothing is changing over here.
显而易见，这里什么都没变
Now, what's interesting is it is in fact seguing, and
现在，有趣的是事实上它已经 segue 了，并且
it is replacing that.
替换了 MVC
The only problem is, we didn't prepare that thing
唯一的问题是，我们还没为对应的操作设置
to show the right emotion before it showed, so
准备展示对应的心情，所以
it is just showing the neutral emotion.
它仅仅只是展示了初始的心情
It's creating a new MVC, but it's just showing neutral,
它创建了一个新的 MVC，但是仅仅只是展示了初始的心情
because it has not been prepared to be onscreen.
因为它还没设置准备些什么来显示在屏幕上
We have to go back to the emotions view controller here,
我们要回到这个 EmotionsViewController 里
and do this prepare for segue, and prepare that destination
然后完成这个 prepare(for segue:) 函数，并且
detail view controller to do what we want it to do.
让目标细节控制器来准备完成我们想要它做的事情
Let's get rid of some of the comments here,
让我们忽略一些这里的注释
just to make our code a little cleaner.
为了让我们的代码干净一些
And get rid of that, as well.
把这个也忽略
Actually, we can even get rid of that.
事实上，我们甚至可以忽略那个
Okay, so here's our prepare for
好啦，这就是我们的 prepare(for segue:)
segue with this extra argument sender,
并带一个额外的叫做 sender 的参数了
which I'll also talk about in a little bit.
也就是我待会儿会讲的东西
So what do we do when we prepare for segue?
那么我们准备 segue 时做些什么呢？
There's usually two really important piece of information
通常在准备 segue 到一个 MVC 的时候
we need when we're preparing to segue to an MVC.
有两个非常重要的信息
One is we need to know which segue, tha's the identifier.
一个是我们要知道是哪一个 segue，也就是需要标识符
The other one we need to know is what is the new MVC
另一个需要知道的是 segue 到的新的 MVC
that this system just created for
也就是那个由这个系统刚创建的
us that we're supposed to prepare.
我们需要让它做好准备的那个 MVC
Both of these things are found inside this
这两个东西都能在这个参数里找到
argument right here, this segue, this UIStoryboardSegue,
这个叫做 segue 的参数，这个属于 UIStoryboardSegue 类的
if we ALT click on it.
如果我按住 alt 然后点击它的话
Can't get it.
啊噢，没有东西
Sorry about that, here we go, on this guy.
不好意思点错了，是这一个
We have the storyboard segue, and
我们有一个 UIStoryboardSegue 的类，并且
if you'll look in the documentation for it,
如果你在文档里查的话
you'll see that it doesn't have a lot in there.
你能看到它内部其实没有多少东西
But one important thing is the destination view controller,
但是一个重要的事是这个 var destination: UIViewController
and one is the identifier of the segue.
另一个是这个 var identifier: String?
This is also the source,
还有这一个 var source: UIViewController
which would be the emotions view controller.
也就是那个 EmotionsViewController
That's really just got the information
这些就是得到了那些
that we need to prepare this thing.
我们需要用来 prepare 的东西
Let's go and first get the destination view controller.
首先我们先得到那个目标控制器
I'm gonna say let destinationViewController
let destinationViewController
equal the segue's destination.
= segue.destination
So I've got that view controller.
那么我得到了那个视图控制器
Now that is a type UI view controller, if I alt-click on
那么它现在是一个 UIViewController 类的，如果我按住 alt 再点击
that, you'll see it's type UI view controller.
你能看到它是 UIViewController 类的
That's because segue is this generic UI stroyboard thing,
那是因为这个参数 segue 是一个普通的 UIStoryboardSegue 类
it doesn't know anything about face view controllers,
它不知道任何关于 FaceViewController 的东西
EmotionViewController, anything like that.
或者 EmotionsViewController，之类的
So, we're gonna have to actually use that casting
所以我将使用 as
mechanism with as.
来实现转换机制
Remember that as casting that we did with Any, in AnyObject?
还记得用 as 对 Any 或者 AnyObject 进行类型转换吗？
We're gonna have to do it here,
这里我们也要这么做
because this destinationViewController
因为这个 destinationViewController
better darn well be a face view controller, or
最好是一个 FaceViewController，否则
I don't know how to prepare it.
我就不知道该怎么 prepare 它了
That's the only thing I know how to prepare,
这是我唯一知道如何准备
this emotion for us, so it'd better be that.
展示我们心情图的东西，所以它最好是那个
So I'm gonna say, if I can let a FaceViewController equal
所以这里我会写，if let faceViewController =
the destinationViewController as, and
destinationViewController as?
I'm gonna do it conditionally here, a FaceViewController.
我这里会添加条件，FaceViewController
Then, I'm good to go.
接下来，就可以开始了
So now remember, this as kinda conditionally checks to see if
记住了，这个 as 是一个条件像是用来检查
it's possible for this to be a FaceViewController.
这个是否是一个 FaceViewController 的
And if it's not, my preparer's gonna do nothing.
并且如果不是的话，我的 prepare 就不会做任何事
And it's gonna let that destination view controller
然后它就会让那个目标视图控制器
appear unprepared,
展现出没有处理过的样子
because it doesn't know how to prepare it.
因为我不知道如何准备它
Cuz we only know how to prepare, (at least so far in
因为目前来说
our app), we only know how to prepare a FaceViewController.
在这个 app 上，我们只知道如何准备一个 FaceViewController
Okay, in fact some would say don't use, as, with,
好，事实上有些人会说这里不要使用 as 和
if let, here.
if-let
Just use as exclamation point, and make your program crash if
只要使用 as! 就可以，然后就会当你 segue
you try to segue to something you're not expecting.
到一个你不想要的东西的时候造成程序崩溃
Cuz again, you'll find it when you're debugging
因为再一次的，在上线程序之前的 debug 调试环节
before you ship your product.
你就会发现有错误
So I can see the argument for that.
我能理解这种观点
But we'll make it so we'll just ignore it, if we can't
但是这里我们如果我们不能把目标 MVC
convert that destination to a face view controller.
转换为一个 FaceViewController 的话就暂时忽略它
Alright, so now let's check the identifier.
好的，现在我们来检查 identifier
One thing about the identifier is someone might have
关于 identifier 的一点是有时候可能
forgotten to set it in the storyboard.
会忘记在 storyboard 中设置它
So I'm gonna do an if let on it.
所以我这里会用 if-let
if let identifier = segue.identifier.
if let identifier = segue.identifier
Cuz this segue.identifier right here,
因为这个这里的 segue.identifier
you can see is an optional string.
你能看到它是一个可选字符串
So it might be not set, in the storyboard.
所以它可能在 storyboard 中没有设置
So I'm checking to make sure that it is in fact set.
所以我在检查以核对它是否被设置
And now I need the expression, the facial expression,
现在我需要那个 Expression，那个 FacialExpression
that I'm gonna set in this space for,
也就是我在这个括号里要设置的东西
this is where I'm gonna do the actual preparing.
这就是我会做准备工作的地方
And I could do a little switch, or an if then, else,
我可以用 switch 或 if-else 语句
if then, else here on all the different segues: sad,
来对应不同的 segue: sad
happy, worried.
Happy，Worried
But I'm imagining that " my app might have 20 or
但是我觉得：“我的 app 可能有一天会有
30 emotions someday".
20 或 30 个表情”
As such, I wanted to do something a little more
这样的话，我想要让它有一些可扩展性
extensible, similar to what we did with the calculator brains
跟我们在 CalculatorBrain 中的操作很像
operation, which is I'm going to create a private
也就是我将创建一个私有的
little dictionary here called Emotional Faces.
叫做 emotionalFaces 的字典
And it's going to a dictionary that has Strings as the keys,
这将是一个以 String 为键，以
and Facial Expressions Facial expressions, FacialExpression.
FacialExpression
Oops, sorry this was supposed to be colon
不好意思这里应该是冒号
FacialExpression as the values.
FacialExpression 为值的字典
I'm even gonna just put the values in right here.
我将把值放在这里
So this is just a little dictionary.
那么这就是一个小字典
This string is gonna be the identifier here
这里的 String 就是 identifier
that comes back, the name of our segue.
也就是 segue 的名字
And the FacialExpression is gonna be the facial expression
然后这个 FacialExpression 就将是我想要
that I want to use there.
使用的对应的面部表情
What's it complaining about here?
这个报错是什么？
Cuz I didn't have any in there.
噢是我还没放进东西
Yeah, cuz we have nothing in here.
对的，这个报错就是因为字典里还没有东西
So let's put some things in here.
那么让我们放些进去吧
Let's do sad.
创建 sad
What's a good facial expression for sad?
悲伤的面部表情什么才好？
Well let's create one,
让我们来创建一个吧
a facial expression where the eyes are probably
一个有着可能是闭上眼睛
closed eyes, and the mouth is in a frown.
然后嘴巴撅起的面部表情
That sounds pretty sad all around.
听起来真的很悲伤
And then for happy,
接下来是开心
it'd probably be the facial expression with the eyes open
应该是一个眼睛睁开
and we'll let the mouth in a big smile, of course.
嘴上有着一个大的微笑的面部表情，当然了
And I think that worried,
然后我觉得那个担心的话
I looked at a few facial expressions.
我面部表情看得少
I thought, worried, the best thing that looks like that was
我觉得吧，担心的话，最好的应该是
eyes open, and the mouth kind of in a, a little smirk.
眼睛睁开，然后嘴巴的话撅起
That face, for some reason to me, looks a little worried.
那个表情，某种意义上对我来说，看起来就是有点担心
Now I've got this table,
现在我有了这个表
which I can add more things to over time.
之后可以再添加东西
And all I have to do is make a new segue for it, and
我要做的就是创建一个新的 segue 然后
have the identifier match the string here.
让它的 identifier 匹配这里的字符串
Now, I might have an identifier that's not in here,
现在，我可能有一个不在这个表内的 identifier
so I'm gonna say if I can let the expression I want equal
所以我就会写 if let expression =
My emotionalFace is here, sub the identifier.
emotionalFaces[identifier]
So I'm looking it up there.
然后它就会去那个字典里查找
But it might come back nil cuz we know that if we
但是它也有可能返回 nil 因为我们知道的
look something up in dictionary it's not there,
如果我们在字典里找一些不存在的东西的话
it will come back nil.
它就会返回 nil
So that time we're doing if let.
所以那样的话我们就需要使用 if-let
By the way, look at this I have, if let this,
顺带一提，看看这些 if-let
if let that, if let this.
非常多
And you can imagine to having four or five of these, and
你可以想象假如有四五个的话，并且
you start getting really deep, and
你开始想要深入代码结构的话
the code is really kinda messy.
这些代码看起来就会很乱
You can actually just do these with commas.
其实你可以只用逗号来完成这些
You can just put right here, this one, and then a comma,
你可以仅仅只是把这一个放在这里，然后接下来是一个逗号
and then this one, and then a comma.
然后再这个，接一个逗号
So you can put as many of these things as you want.
这样你就可以想要几个放几个
And not just lets, you know, if let comma, let comma, but
不仅仅是 let，你知道的，if-let 加逗号， let 加逗号
also other expressions too, other things.
其他的表达式也可以
Like, it's almost like an ampersand kind of expression.
相当于是 && 表达式
And then makes it so
然后这样的话
that I don't need all these curly braces.
我就不需要这些大括号了
I can just use this one top level curly brace.
我只要用到这一个最顶层的大括号就行
Now I have the expression.
现在我有这个表达式了
Here is where I'm gonna do the prepare.
然后就要在这里完成准备
I'm gonna say FaceViewController,
我将输入 faceViewController
prepare yourself by making your model,
准备好它自己，也就是
the expression equal this expression
让它的模型 faceViewController.expression = expression
that I just looked up in that table.
也就是在表格里找到的那个 expression
So that's the actual prepare.
所以这就是真正的准备了
That is where I am preparing this new MVC that it
这就是我准备这个刚创建的 MVC 的地方了
created, this brand new FaceViewController I just
这个我刚刚用 segue 创建的
created with the segue.
崭新的 FaceViewController
I'm preparing it to do what it does.
我把它准备好后来完成它的任务
So let's see if that works.
那么我们来看看是否生效吧
The face should be prepared now.
那个脸表情应该已经被准备好了
When it gets created, we should see a face.
当新的 MVC 创建时，我们能看到一个脸
The right face.
和脸对应的表情
Okay, so here it is.
好，这就是了
Let's try.
我们来试试看
Woo-hoo, happy.
哇哦，开心
Well, it looks a little worried, and sad.
它看起来有点担心，然后是伤心
Now, let's see how happy we are, though, on an iPhone.
现在我们来看看在一台 iPhone 上有多开心
Because we know that on an iPhone, it's kinda small.
因为我们知道在一台 iPhone 上的话，它会有一点小
Split View, not really enough room for a Split View.
不会有足够的空间给一个分屏控制器的
So what's gonna happen with this storyboard on an iPhone?
那么这个 storyboard 在 iPhone 上会发生什么呢？
Let's find out.
我们来看看
Okay, well, here we go, Sad, Happy, Worried.
开始吧，Sad，Happy，Worried 三个按钮都在
Excellent, let's see Happy.
完美，那么我们点击 Happy
All right, we're happy.
不错，我们有 Happy 的脸了
Well, now we're not so
但是现在我们有点不开心了
happy because we can't get out of here.
因为我们离不开这个界面
We got this happy face but I can't get it back.
我们虽然得到了这个 Happy 的脸但我们离不开了
Let's try going, well, even in landscape, no Split View, so
我们试试，好吧，即使是横屏模式，也没有分屏
now there's no way to get back to pick any other expression.
那么现在没有任何方法能回到选择脸部表情的界面了
So in the iPhone, you get to pick one expression and
所以在 iPhone 里，你只能选择一种表情然后
you're done, and that's the end of the app.
就结束了，也就是这个 app 的终点了
You have to quit the app now because, or
你现在必须退出这个 app
turn your phone off, I guess.
或者关掉你的手机，我猜
There's absolutely nothing you can do.
因为很明显你已经没有什么能做的了
You're stuck. I guess you can make
你卡在了那里，我猜你能让
the eyes blink.
眼睛眨一眨
That's about it.
大概就这样了
So this is not a very good app on the iPhone, obviously.
所以很显然这不是一个 iPhone 上的好 app
So what are we gonna do?
那么我们要怎么做呢？
Since we have no Split View on the iPhone,
既然我们在 iPhone 上没有分屏控制器
(you actually can have a Split View on the iPhone by the way,
顺带一提，事实上你可以在 iPhone 上加一个分屏控制器
but you have to do a special stuff to kinda enable it.
但是你需要做一些特殊的事情来启用它
But by default the Split View doesn't work.
但是默认情况下分屏控制器是没有作用的
Well, of course, Apple understands that.
当然了，Apple 公司明白这一点
That Split View is not very good for iPhones.
也就是分屏控制器对 iPhone 来说不是很好
iPhone Plus is by the way, it does work, and
iPhone Plus 的话，是可以有效果的
I'm gonna show you that in a moment.
我之后演示给你们看
They know it's not that good.
Apple 公司知道效果不好
So if you go back to your storyboard here.
所以如果你回到这个 storyboard 的话
We're gonna go back to our storyboard,
我们回到我们的 storyboard
and we're gonna look at this.
然后我们看看这个
And we're gonna say, hmm, well, on iPhone,
然后会想，好吧，在 iPhone 上
I'd really like this UI to be navigation controller instead,
我会想要让这个 UI 界面变成导航控制器好了
not a Split View.
不用分屏控制器
Navigation Controller where when I click on this emotion
用导航控制器也就是当我点击选择的表情的话
it chose the face by sliding it on top, but
控制器就会把对应的脸滑动到顶层，但是
I'll have a back button so
我能得到一个返回按钮那么
I can go back, pick a different one.
我就可以返回了，然后再选择一个不同的表情
It'll slide it on top and I can hit back,
它就会再把对应的表情滑动到顶层并且我还可以点击返回
you see what I mean, so I can go back and forth.
你们懂我意思了吗，这样的话我就可以返回也可以继续了
And you can do that incredibly simply.
并且实现的方法非常简单
You just pick this view control right here, and
你只要选择这个视图控制器，然后
go to editor.
点击 Editor
Embed in Navigation Controller.
选择 Embed In 再选择 Navigation Controller
And it's gonna insert a Navigation Controller
然后它就会插入一个导航控制器
in the middle there, see that,
在它们中间，看
how I put that Navigation Controller in there.
我是如何在那里加入一个导航控制器的
And what's really cool is with the Navigation Controller you
导航控制器真正酷的是
actually get a little title bar, and you can go straight
你能得到一个小的标题栏，然后在
here in interface builder if you want and
这里的 Interface Builder 中，如果你想要的话
put a title in there like maybe emotions.
你可以直接在上面放一个例如叫做 Emotions 的标题
We could call it, it's the name of our app or
我们可以这么取名，可以叫做我们 app 的名字或者
that's what these are in this MVC rather, so
就这个 MVC 的内容
I'll put a little title in there, and that's really cool.
那么我会在那里放一个小标题，这会很酷
And so now when we run, I get my face coming up in neutral
现在当我运行的时候，就会得到面无表情的脸
mode, and if I go back, now I can pick something like happy.
并且如果我返回的话，我可以选择例如 Happy 这样的选项
Now one thing you might be interested in there is like,
现在那里可能有一个东西让你感兴趣
whoa, it came up in neutral mode.
哇哦，它是以面无表情出现的
Instead of coming up on this page, you kinda would expected
而不是以这个页面出现，你可能期待
it to come up on this page., wouldn't you?
是用这个页面来出现，是吗？
And we actually made it extra credit for
事实上我们有一些额外奖励来让你们
you to go to figure out how to do it.
自己去探究如何先展示这个页面
And what you need to
然后你要做的是一些
do is something with Split View Controller.
跟分屏控制器有关的东西
It's delegate, which I'm not gonna talk about the delegates
其实是周三我会讲的代理
until Wednesday, that's why we made it extra credit.
星期三之前我不会讲，所以作为加分题
But you're gonna use Split View's delegate and
但是你将使用分屏视图的代理
read the documentation, and you can make it so
阅读文档，这样你就能实现代理
that it'll come up on either page.
让 app 能以任意的页面出现
Either on this detailed page or on this master page.
无论是这个细节页面或者是这个主页面
But you can see that this is working great, in fact we've
但是你能看到它还是有效果的，事实上
even got this nice little title bar up here, and we can
我们甚至得到了这个不错的小标题栏在上面，然后我们可以
switch back and forth between any emotions that we want.
在我们想要的任意表情之间切换
And let's go see what happened when we did that to iPad.
然后我们来看看在 iPad 上的话会发生什么吧
Did we break the iPad?
iPad 上会出错吗？
Let's hope we didn't break the iPad by doing that.
希望不会出错
Here we go.
来吧
It comes up.
它出现了
There's the face.
那就是脸表情
By the way, you can do Split Views in Portrait.
顺带一提，竖屏模式下也可以有分屏效果
You just slide out.
只要滑出来
You see, it slides out like a little shelf like that.
看到没，它就像个小柜子一样滑出来
Or you can rotate and see them side by side.
或者你也可以旋转后看他们紧贴在一起
And it's still working.
并且仍然有效果
So the iPad is working just fine.
所以在 iPad 上工作很顺畅
Well, unfortunately,
啊倒霉
there's no zoom level that's a better zoom level.
这个尺寸不好，这个尺寸好一些了
But the iPad has a title here.
但是 iPad 的这里有一个标题
But it'd be really cool if there was
如果这里也有一个标题的话
a title over here, too.
就会很棒
Like maybe this would say, sad and
例如这里会显示 Sad 然后
if I hit happy it would say, happy over here.
如果我点击 Happy 的话就会显示 Happy 在这里
Wouldn't that be cool?
不是很酷吗？
To have a title on both sides of that, that's
为了在两边都有标题
often in a Split View that we want, because you want kind of
通常在分屏情况下我们都想要这样，因为
the balance between the two to have tittle on both sides.
两边都有标题均衡一些
So no problem, let's just go back to our storyboard here,
那么没问题，让我们回到我们的 storyboard
and select this View Controller and
然后选择这个视图控制器并且
embed it in a Navigation Controller.
把它嵌入一个导航控制器
And in fact, if we go here and look at an iPad.
事实上，如果我们点击这里然后选择 iPad
What it's gonna look like on iPad, especially in landscape?
在 iPad 上看起来会怎么样，尤其是横屏模式？
We'll see that,
我们能看到
ooh, this is looking what like exactly what we want.
噢，看起来跟我们想要的一模一样
Look. See,
看
when it's in detail, its got a title bar, a title bar here,
在细节视图里，它有一个标题栏，这里
title bars there.
那里也有
It's fantastic, this is gonna be great.
很完美，肯定会成功
Let's do it.
我们试试
All right, look at that, title bar on the top.
看那里，顶部有标题栏
And, uh-oh, we broke it.
然后，啊哦，app 失效了
What happened there?
那里发生了什么？
Why did we break that?
我们为什么让它出问题了
Well, this has to do with the preparation piece.
这些跟准备那部分有关
And I talked about this in the lecture last time.
并且我上一次课中讲到过
Because what prepare is doing is,
因为我们的准备工作做的是
it's creating a new MVC here, and then we're preparing it.
它在这里创建了一个新的 MVC，然后再准备它
The problem is that now when it creates a new MVC here,
现在的问题是当它创建一个新的 MVC 的时候
what is the MVC?
那个 MVC 是什么类型的？
What kind of MVC is it?
什么种类的？
Anyone want to hazard a guess?
有没有人想试着猜一猜？
Cuz it's not a face view controller
因为它不是一个 FaceViewController
anymore, what is it?
有人想回答吗？它是什么？
Yeah, it's a UI navigation controller.
对的，它是一个 UINavigationController
That's the new MVC we're creating,
这就是我们正在创建的新的 MVC
it has a faceView in it, but
它里面有一个 FaceViewController 但是
it's still a UI navigation controller.
它本身仍然是一个 UINavigationController
So our code that we have back here.
所以回到这里我们的这些代码
That's doing this prepare.
这个 prepare 方法
It says, if I can let the faceView
这里写着，如果能把 faceViewController 赋值为
equal the destination as a FaceViewController.
转换成 FaceViewController 类型的 destinationViewController
Well, I can't do that because it's not.
所以，这个不会执行，因为它不是
It's a UI navigation controller instead.
它是一个 UINavigationController
And I'll show you that in debugging here.
我调试给你们看
Let's go ahead and set a break point right here, and
让我们在这里设置一个断点，然后
go back over here and pick one, like happy.
回到这里并选择一个，例如 Happy
Here it breaks.
然后这里程序就暂停了
And if we look at this DestinationViewController,
如果我们看这个 destinationViewController 的话
those of you who came to the debugging Friday section.
那些周五来调试课的同学
We didn't really go over this cool feature, but
我们没讲到这个很棒的特点，但是
if you just mouse over a variable.
如果你把鼠标放到这个变量上的话
You see how I just,
你看到我如何做的吗
I'm holding my mouse over DestinationViewController?
我把鼠标放在 destinationViewController 变量上，看到吗？
You see it's showing that there?
你看到它展示的东西了吗？
There's two really cool buttons in there.
那里有两个很棒的按钮
You see this one looks like an eye?
你们看到这个像是眼睛的按钮了吗？
And this one looks like the letter i for info.
还有这个像是获得更多信息时候用的 i 的按钮
If you click the one that looks like a eye, it'll actually
如果你点击这个像是眼睛的按钮的话，事实上
show you that View Controller right there in the debugger.
它会在调试器中展现给你那个 destinationViewController
Which is kinda cool.
很酷
And if you go over here and click the other little i,
如果你点击另一个小 i 按钮的话
it'll show you the class that it is.
它就会展示它是什么类
In this case, it's a UI navigation controller.
在现在这种情况下，它是一个 UINavigationController
And this works for all kinds of types,
这种方法适用于所有类型
colors, even a map location.
颜色，甚至是表的位置
It'll show you a map with the location on there.
它会展示带地址的表
So this little mouseover debugging thing is
所以这个小小的鼠标移动调试
really cool.
很酷
But anyway, we see that DestinationViewController
但是无论如何，我们看到那个 destinationViewController
right there is a UI navigation controller.
是一个 UINavigationController
We know that's no good.
我们知道这不好
So what are we gonna do about this?
那么这里我们该怎么办呢？
Well, I'm gonna check for this case, okay?
我要为这种情况检查一下，对吗？
I'm gonna say, if I can let navigationController equal
我这里写 if let navigationController = destinationViewController
the destinationViewController as a UINavigationController,
as? UINavigationController
in other words,
也就是说
if that destination is a UI Navigation Controller, then
如果目标 MVC 是一个 UINavigationController 的话，那么
I'm gonna grab the visible ViewController out of it and
我将把它的可见的视图控制器抓取出来然后
use that as the FaceViewController hopefully.
把它作为 FaceViewController
So, I'm gonna say in this case I want
那么如果是这一种 if 的情况的话
the destinationViewController, which is this thing up here,
我想要这个 destinationViewController，也就是这里的这个常量
which now it needs to be a var and so
现在需要它成为一个变量因为
I'm gonna change its value here.
在这里我要改变它的值
I'm gonna let that equal,
然后 destinationViewController 赋值为
the navigationController's visibleViewController.
navigationController 的可见视图控制器
Okay, now this is great,
好的，现在这样就可以了
visibleViewController is a really nice method and
.visibleViewController 是一个很好的方法（属性）
navigation control, it shows you whichever
和导航控制，它能展示给你
card stack is currently visible, exactly what I want.
究竟哪个视图是可见的，也就是我需要的那个
The only problem with it, however, is it returns
现在唯一的问题是它会返回一个
an optional, because nothing might be visible in
可选值，因为在导航控制器中
the navigationController right now.
当前可能没有东西是可见的
Okay, you might have never put anything
也就是说可能没有放任何东西
in the navigationController.
在导航控制器里
So since that is an optional, I'm gonna have to give it
那么既然它是一个可选值，我将必须给它
some default value, and the default value,
一个默认值
I'm just gonna say, just use the destinationViewController
就直接使用 destinationViewController 吧
as is if I can't get the visible ViewController or
用作如果我得不到可见的视图控制器或者
the navigationController.
导航控制器的时候的默认值
So it's kinda a default to use what it already was.
所以默认情况下就是它自身
Basically, don't change it.
不会改变它自己
So this little if is nice, because now my code works if
所以这一个 if 语句很有用，因为现在我的代码
it's in a navigationController or even if it's not.
在处于导航控制器中或者不是都能正常工作
Because if it's not in a navigationController,
因为如果它不在导航控制器中的话
this is gonna do nothing.
这个 if 语句就什么都不会做
That's going to fail.
这个 if 判断会失败
Alright, this as is not going to work.
这个 as 就不会生效
And we'll go straight down to checking
然后代码就会跳过然后执行下面的 if
if it's a FaceViewControllor.
来判断它是不是一个 FaceViewController
So if I later came along back to my storyboard here and
那么如果回到 storyboard 并且
I decided,
决定
eh, you know what, I don't really want the title on here.
事实上我不想要那个标题栏了
And I took this navigationController out
然后我拿走了这个导航控制器
of the picture, my code would still work, cuz my code works
我的代码也可以工作，因为我的代码
whether I'm going straight to a FaceController or
已经写成无论是连接到一个 FaceViewController 或者
through a navigationController.
一个 UINavigationController 都能工作
Let's see if that indeed fixed our problem.
让我们来看看它是否真的解决了我们的问题吧
Here we go, let's try it.
开始，我们试一下
Happy, yeah, worried, sad.
三个都行耶
Happy, we're happy that it's working.
Happy 也有，能正常运行真令人开心
Okay, now we have this nice title bar at the top and
好，现在顶部有一个标题栏
we said, wouldn't it be cool if we could put a title, so
我们曾经说过，如果这里放一个标题会很酷
let's do that.
那么开始做吧
Let's put a little title here,
让我们在这里放一个小标题
in fact the title I'm gonna put here is whichever button
事实上这里我要放的标题是调用对应 MVC 按钮的
brought this MVC up.
标题
So if the sad button brought it up,
所以如果 Sad 按钮调用了对应的 MVC
I'm gonna get its current title and put it up here,
我就会得到它现在的标题然后把它放在这里
kinda like we did in the calculator.
像是 Calculator demo 中做的那样
Look back to the sender and luckily prepare for segue,
查看 sender 里的东西，幸运的是 prepare(for segue:)
has the sender.
方法里有 sender 参数
This is the thing that cause the segue to happen.
这就是导致 segue 发生的东西
Which is going to be one of those buttons.
也就是那些按钮中的一个
So right down here, I can just get the current title of this
那么在这里，我能得到这个 sender 的标题
sender right here and set that to be the title.
并且把它设置到标题栏里
Now if you remember from the lecture about
现在如果你记得关于导航控制器那节课的话
navigationController, the way that you
在导航控制器中
set things that appear when it's in a navigationController
设置那些能显示的东西的方法
like the title, you can also set the buttons,
例如标题，也可以设置按钮
the back button title you can set,
返回按钮可以设置
or you can even put write buttons in the top.
甚至可以在顶部设置读写按钮
You do that with this thing called NavigationItem on
那个方法就是调用 UIViewController 里的
UIViewController.
navigationItem
So I'm gonna take the faceViewController's
那么我这里要用到 faceViewController.navigationItem
navigationItem, which, by the way the navigationItem,
顺带一提，navigationItem
you can just kind of think of it as
你可以把它当作是
a bag of goodies that only UINavigationController uses.
一些只有 UINavigationCOntroller 使用的东西
And it only looks in that bag of goodies
而且仅当
when this ViewController, the faceViewController,
这个 faceViewController 是
is the visible ViewController in the NavigationController.
这个 UINavigationController 里可见的视图控制器时
Then it looks in this bag of goodies and you can see that
它才会看这个包里的东西
there's a lot of things in the bag of goodies,
你能看到，这个包里有很多东西
like leftBarButtonItem, rightBarButtonItems, and
像是 leftBarButtonItem，rightBarButtonItems，当然还有
of course the title.
title
Which is what I want to set here.
也就是我现在要设置的东西
I want to set the title of the navigationController
我想要设置这个导航控制器的标题为
when this thing is visible.
当这个东西是可见的时候
And I'm gonna send it,
我就把它设置为
I want to send it to the sender's current title, but
我想要把它设置为 sender 的当前标题，但是
I can't quite do that.
这样是没用的
Why can't I do that?
为什么呢？
Why is that not gonna work?
为什么这么写不会生效？
This.
这个
See any problem?
看出什么问题了吗？
Yeah, this is Any.
对的，这是一个 Any 类型的
And Any does not understand any messages.
并且 Any 类型的东西不懂任何消息
Because it doesn't know what it is.
因为它不知道自己是什么
So we have to take this any and turn it into a UI button.
所以我们必须把这个 Any 转换为 UIButton
And we do that by saying this, sender as the UIButton.
我们是通过这么写，sender as? UIButton
Now we could almost send current title.
现在我们可以发送当前标题了
The only problem is this.
唯一的问题是
What is this type of,
这是什么类型的
what is the type of, if I can select it, this expression?
这个表达式，会是什么类型的结果？
What's its type?
它是什么类型的呢？
No one wanna guess on this one?
没人想猜一猜吗？
No one?
没有吗？
It's an optional, right?
它是一个可选值，对吗？
Because "as?" returns an optional, so this is
因为 as? 返回一个可选值，所以
an optional, so we can't send an optional current title.
它是一个可选值，所以我们不能发送一个是可选值的当前标题
We need to either exclamation point it, or
我们需要要么用 ！ 来拆包，或者
a little safer, we could optional chain it.
用更安全的，可选链
Because we know that optional chaining is just going to
因为我们知道可选链能在
ignore the rest of this expression if that happened to
它不是一个 UIButton 的时候忽略整一个
not be a button.
表达式
And this as returned nil,
并且返回 nil
because this couldn't be turned into a button.
因为这个不能转换为 UIButton
So we'll just optional chain in which case the title here
所以在这个标题可能为 nil 的情况下我们只要使用可选链就好
will be set to nil, because this whole thing will be nil
因为这里如果这里可选链的条件没被触发的话
if this optional chaining doesn't happen.
整一个表达式都会是 nil
And that's okay,
这种情况是可以的
because we look at the title of a navigation item.
因为我们看这个 navigationItem 的 tile 变量
It's an optional.
可以看到它是可选的
So we can send it to a nil.
所以我们可以发送给它 nil 值
And then this will, it will have no title up there.
然后标题栏上也就不会有标题了
I intentionally put this thing in here for
我故意把这个放在这里
lot of things going on here.
因为这里发生了很多事情
We have the any cast going on.
我们有 Any?
We have optional chaining going on here.
然后这里是它的可选链
We use the navigation item.
我们使用到了 navigationItem
So there is a lot in this line of code.
所以这一行代码里有很多信息
So make sure you kind of understand what's
确保你们能明白
all the pieces going on there.
那里都发生了些什么
Now we should be getting hopefully the title of
那么现在希望在右边部分的 MVC
the button appearing as the title on the right-hand side.
能有按钮的标题出现吧
So happy, sure enough, there's happy.
那么点击 Happy，Happy 标题出现了
Worried, there's worried.
Worried，标题也出现了
Sad, happy.
点 Sad，点 Happy
And of course if we rotate,
当然了如果我们旋转的话
we're still getting the title up there.
也能得到那些标题
We can slide this thing out and pick sad,
我们可以划拉出这个东西然后选择 Sad
and it happens back there.
然后那里就发生变化了
Slide that thing out of the way if we want.
如果需要的话还可以划回去
Rotate back.
旋转回去
How about iPhone 7?
那么 iPhone7 上效果如何呢？
Let's see if we've
让我们来看看
broken that.
我们是否毁了它
It appears with this split views detail coming up first
它一开始细节视图显示的
in this neutral mode.
是面无表情的脸
We'll go back to emotions.
回到 Emotions
Pick Happy.
选择 Happy
Sure enough, it's setting that title fine there as well.
设置标题成功
If we go here.
如果我们切到横屏模式
Since it's an iPhone, can't do split view,
由于它是一台 iPhone，不能分屏
it's still working fine in navigationController mode.
它仍然可以在导航控制器模式下正常工作
Let's go look at a 7 Plus.
我们看看 iPhone7 Plus 效果如何
There is a 7 plus which is kind of a high breed
iPhone7 Plus 是 iPhone7 跟 iPad
between iPhone 7 and an iPad.
之间的过渡
And in portrait mode,
在竖屏模式下
an iPhone 7 plus works just like an iPhone.
iPhone7 Plus 就像一台 iPhone 一样工作
So it's gonna be the
所以就是导航控制器
navigationController back and forth.
来回调度
But in landscape, it'll work like an iPad.
但是在横屏模式下，它就像 iPad 一样工作
Okay, so obviously an iPhone 7 plus in portrait mode,
所以很明显，竖屏模式下的 iPhone7 Plus
it is not big enough to do the slide-out thing like an iPad
没有足够的空间来像 iPad 的横屏模式下那样滑动东西
does in portrait mode, but in landscape mode it is, so
但是在横屏模式它就有空间了
let's make it so this thing fits.
现在我们来把尺寸调整对
That's close enough to fitting.
差不多适合了
I'll go small here.
我再调小一点吧
All right, so this is a plus.
好了，那么这就是一台 iPhone7 Plus
And you can see it comes up in portrait mode.
然后你可以看到它以竖屏模式展示
It's acting like it's an iPhone.
表现地就像一台 iPhone
See that, okay?
看到没？
It's just doing that.
就是这样
But look what happens if I go to landscape mode,
但是如果切到横屏模式看看会发生什么
I get a split view.
我得到了一个分屏视图
Tha's working fine.
也能正常工作
So see how we built in the storyboard this hybrid UI and
那么你们看到我之前在 storyboard 中如何创建这个混合 UI 界面并且
it works on all the different kinds of devices.
能在不同设备上运行的方法了吧
No matter what they control with you or
无论你用什么操作
not it'll default go back to using
默认情况下它都会使用
navigationController, whatever.
导航控制器
And the only thing we had to do in our code
唯一我们需要在代码中做的
as a concession to the cross-platform is checking for
跨平台的事情就是
that navigationController and only for
检查那个导航控制器还有那个
the thing we were segueing to.
我们 sugue 的东西
Back to the slides.
回到幻灯片
Our next topic here is the View Controller Lifecycle.
我们下一个主题是视图控制器的生命周期
Now, everything has a life cycle,
每一样东西都有生命周期
even we have a life cycle: we're born, we live our lives,
即使我们也有：我们出生，生活
things happen, and we die.
各种事情发生，然后我们死亡
Well, that happens to a View Controller as well.
视图控制器也是这样
It's just born, things happen to it, and then it dies,
就是出生，然后发生了些事情，接着它死亡了
it leaves the heap.
并且离开了堆
That's what happens on its death.
它死亡的时候会发生的事情
Why do we care about the view controller lifecycle?
为什么我们要在意视图控制器的生命周期呢？
Because we often wanna do things at various key
因为通常我们想要在它生命周期中的关键转折点
inflection points in its lifetime.
做一些事情
The start of a lifecycle is really simple.
生命周期的开始很简单
It gets initialized, and 99.99% of
它被初始化，并且 99.99% 的情况下
the time a view controller is coming out of a storyboard.
一个视图控制器会出现在 storyboard 中
Its initializer is this special initializer coming out
它的构造器就是这个 storyboard 中出现的
of a storyboard.
这个特殊的构造器
In your reading assignments,
在你们的作业中
I actually explained how this works.
我已经解释过它如何工作了
But we don't usually override the initializer of a view
但是我们通常不会重写一个视图控制器
controller.
的构造器
We're going to use the other ways we know to initialize
我们将使用另一个方法来初始化
each variables.
每一个变量
I'm not even gonna talk about how to make one in code.
我甚至不会讲用代码如何实现一个
Because we just, just don't do that.
因为我们通常，不那么做
You can see why, right?
你们知道为什么的，对吧？
Because view controller is complicated.
因为视图控制器很复杂
It's got all the UI, the buttons, and all the stuff.
它得到了所有的 UI 界面，按钮，还有别的东西
You're generally not gonna be making that in code.
一般来说都不会用代码来做到
What happens then after it's created?
那么它创建后发生了什么呢？
The next thing that happens is if it's being segued to,
下一件会发生的事情是如果它被 segue 的话
it gets prepared.
它就会被 prepare
Like when we prepared the FaceView Controller there by
就像我们通过设置它的模型
setting it to model.
来准备那个 FaceViewController
That's the next thing that happens after it's
这就是它被初始化后接下来的
initialized.
事情
Then the next thing that happens is its outlets get set.
接下来下一件事是它的出口（outlet）被设置
So, for the FaceView,
举个例子 FaceView
its FaceView outlet got set after it got prepared.
FaceView 的出口是在它准备好后设置的
Then, it appears and disappears on screen.
接着，这个视图控制器在屏幕上就会出现还有消失
In our example right there, the master
我们的那个例子中，主视图控制器
was constantly appearing and disappearing on screen.
就重复着在屏幕上出现和消失
Every time, on the iPhone, for example, that we hit happy or
举个例子，在 iPhone 上，每一次当我们点击 Happy 或者
sad, it would disappear.
Sad 的时候，它就消失
And the face one would come on.
然后那个脸图就会出现
And then, we'd hit back and it would reappear.
接着，我们点击返回，那个主视图就会再次出现
By the way, when that happens, the face one didn't disappear.
顺带一提，当那个发生的时候，脸图没有消失
Well, it disappeared and
好吧，视觉上它是消失了
it also got thrown out of the heap.
并且它也从堆中扔了出来
Because we reuse the things we segue to.
因为我们重用了我们 segue 到的东西
But that master, we don't segue to it.
但是那个主视图，我们没有 segue 到它
It sits there as the master in the split view all the time.
它就作为分屏视图中的主视图一直在那
But it's appearing and disappearing on screen.
但是它在屏幕上会出现和消失
So that's a big thing that happens its lifecycle.
所以这就是在它生命周期内的一件大事
Another thing that happens
另外一个会发生的事情
during the life time of it is it's changing its orientation.
是屏幕发生发生了旋转
We're rotating the landscape.
如果我们把设备旋转至横向
We're on a iPad and
如果我们是在 iPad 上
we're sliding it out as a tray in portrait mode and
纵向模式我们需要把主视图像个托盘一样滑出来
then we rotate to landscape and it's sitting on the side.
然后我们又把它旋转至横向模式，它就又出现在那里了
So it's changing its shape.
所以它改变了它自己的形状
Even the face view of the iPad when we're in portrait,
就像在 iPad 上的 FaceView，当它在纵向模式时
it's big, tall and big.
它又高又大
But then we switch to landscape it's kind of more
但是当我们把它旋转至横向模式时，它就变的有点
like a square, and a little smaller.
像个小方块，然后还有点小
So it's always changing geometry.
所以它总是会改变自己的几何形状
And then it could be in a low memory situation as well where
与此同时它也可能处在一种内存紧张的情况下
we need to recovery some memory,
这样我们就需要回收一部分内存
this almost never happens, but I have to mention it.
这种情况几乎从不发生，但是我也得提一下
It's really maybe not even part of the view controller
它甚至可能不存在于控制器的
lifecycle but it's a good place to talk about it,
生命周期中，但是这是个讨论它的好地方
cuz it's not really that important.
因为它其实没那么重要
Let's talk about the messages that
我们来聊聊哪些消息被发送
are sent to invoke methods in your view controller
来调用视图控制器的方法
when these various things happen.
以表明这一些列的事情发生了
So you already know about your outlets being set.
所以你已经知道你的出口变量已经被关联好了
And you can watch that with your did sets,
而且你可以通过你的 didSet 来观察
the property observer, did set.
那个属性观察器，didSet
And you already know about preparing,
你也已经了解了如何准备
I just showed you about that.
就是我刚刚展示给你的那个
So after those two steps are done,
所以当这两步都做完了之后
you're gonna get this message, viewDidLoad.
你就应该会获得信息 viewDidLoad
Super important method.
这是个非常重要的方法
You're only gonna ever receive it once in the lifetime
在你的控制器的整个生命周期中你只会收到一次
of a viewController.
来自它的信息
And it's really where you're gonna put
所以这个方法几乎是你
almost all of your initialization.
完成所有初始化地方
For example, a lot of times here's where you'll call your
举个例子，通常这里是你调用 updateUI
update UI method, the thing that updates your UI from your
那个用模型来更新 UI 的方法的地方
model, very often you're gonna call that in viewDidLoad.
经常你将从 viewDidLoad 中调用它
Cuz now your model is set because it got prepared
因为现在你的模型应该已经被设置，准备好了
probably, and your outlets are set because this is how it
你的出口变量也关联上了
always happens after outlet setting.
因为 viewDidLoad 总是在那之后被调用
Now, one thing not to do in here though.
但是还有一件并不在这里进行的事
Very careful, listen carefully.
非常重要，认真听
Do not do geometry-based things in viewDidLoad.
不要在 viewDidLoad 里设置任何和几何形状相关的东西
Because when viewDidLoad happens,
因为当 viewDidLoad 被执行时
you have not yet had your final geometry established.
你其实还没能完全确定你最后要呈现的几何形状
You don't quite know if you're portrait, landscape,
你并不是十分确定你的设备是纵向还是横向
what device you're on, you don't know yet.
你将要在什么设备上运行，这些你都还不知道
So do not do things with your bounds in viewDidLoad.
所以不要在 viewDidLoad 中做任何关于边界的设置
Many of you will make this mistake so perk up those ears.
你们当中的一些人会犯这个错误，所以竖起耳朵认真听
Do not do that.
不要这么做
I'm gonna show you other methods in the new controller
我会教你们其他的控制器生命周期的方法
lifecycle for doing that but do not it in viewDidLoad.
来做关于几何形状的工作，但是不要在 viewDidLoad 里做这件事
The next thing I said to you, appear and disappearing.
下一个我要说的是，“出现”和“消失”
You're always appearing and disappearing on screen.
你总会在屏幕上进行“出现”和“消失”的动作
When you appear, you're gonna get two messages.
当你“出现”时，你会得到两条信息
The first is viewWillAppear.
第一个是 viewWillAppear
And that's sent to you before you're actually on screen, but
它在你真正要出现在屏幕上之前发送给你
just very very soon going to be,
但是在之前非常短的时间里（发送给你）
guaranteed you're going to be on screen soon.
确保你马上就要出现在屏幕上了
So, what is viewWillAppear for?
所以，这个 viewWillAppear 是干什么的呢？
What are you going to do in a view will appear?
你在这个 viewWillAppear 中要做些什么呢？
Well one thing is if there's anything that changes in your
第一，当你不在屏幕上时
model when you're not on screen,
你模型里有什么东西改变了
maybe your model is a network database or
你的模型可能是一个网络数据库或者
something and it's changing on the screen.
是一个可能在屏幕上变化的什么东西
Then when view appear happens you're going to usually update
当 viewWillAppear 发生时，你通常需要从你的
your UI from your model.
模型中获取信息来更新你的 UI
So maybe you wouldn't do update UI in viewDidLoad,
所以你可能不在 viewDidLoad 中更新你的 UI
you might do it here.
可能你会选择在这里更新
That's if it could change when it's not onscreen.
这是对不在屏幕上时的变化的处理方法
A lot of MVCs,
有很多 MVC
their model only changes when they're onscreen, so
它们的模型只在它们出现在屏幕上时才会改变
you wouldn't have to do anything here.
这样的话你在这就什么也不需要做了
But if your model can be changed out from under you
但是如果你的模型可以在你不在屏幕上时被改变的话
while you're off screen, then you, when you reappear,
那你，在你重新出现的时候
obviously you wanna show the current state of your model.
你显然要展现你模型的确切状态
So that's a good one.
这是个好方法
Another thing you might do in viewWillAppear
还有一件你可能会在 viewWillAppear 中做的事
is start something expensive.
就是开启一些非常耗费资源功能
Because in viewDidLoad you're not guaranteed that you're
因为在 viewDidLoad 中，你不确定你到底会不会
ever gonna come on screen.
出现在屏幕上
There are MVCs that occasionally get loaded up,
有一些 MVC 无意间被加载了
but then the user clicks away somewhere else and
但是用户点了一些其他的地方，因此
you never get shown on screen.
你的 MVC 从来就没有出现在屏幕上
But if viewWillAppear happens,
但是如果 viewWillAppear 发生了
you know you're going on screen.
你确切的知道你会出现在屏幕上
So here you could kick off something expensive.
这时候你就可以开启一些非常耗费资源的功能了
Especially kick off a thread that goes and
比如开启一个
does something expensive in the background.
非常耗费资源的后台进程
Cuz we're gonna talk about multithreading next week and
我们会在下周讲多线程
you're gonna see that anything that takes any amount of time
到时候你就会看到，对于任何花时间和经历
or energy on the part of the processor or the network,
需要耗费处理器资源或者占用网络带宽的东西
you're gonna want to do it in a separate thread.
这些你应该在另一个进程里完成
So you might kick off such a thread here in viewWillAppear.
viewWillAppear 就是创建这种线程的地方
There's also an another method,
还有另外一个方法
viewDidAppear which gets into after you're fully on screen.
viewDidAppear 这个方法在你完全出现在屏幕上之后发送给你
The animation to get you on screen is on screen so
把你带到屏幕上的动画效果已经出现在屏幕上了
you're there.
你也在屏幕上
And what would you do here?
那么在这里你能做些什么呢
There's usually not a lot to do here.
这里通常没那么多事要做
You might start an animation though.
你可能在这开始一个动画效果
You've got some MVC that has some animation going.
你有一些有动画效果的 MVC
And it doesn't make any sense to start it before it
但是这些动画效果没必要在 MVC 出现之前运行
So once it gets on screen then you start it going.
所以当他们出现在屏幕上时
gets on screen.
再开启动画效果
ViewWillAppear and viewDidAppear happen so
viewWillAppear 和 viewDidAppear 发生的时间
close together, it's probably not gonna save much to wait
十分接近，所以在 viewDidAppear 再开始播放动画效果
until viewDidAppear to start the animation,
和在 viewWillAppear 中开始没多大差别
but eh, a lot of people will do that,
但是为了让程序更加明晰
just to kind of for clarity of programming.
很多人选择这样做
And then, of course,
然后，当然啦
you can disappear, and get the same thing there,
你也可以消失。类似的，消失时会调用
a viewWillDisappear and a viewDidDisappear.
viewWillDisappear 和 viewDidDisappear 方法
One thing you notice in all of these view controller
在这你会注意到，所有这些视图控制器
lifecycle is that I'm calling super.
生命周期（方法）中，我都会调用 super
You see that?
你看见了吧
super.viewWillDisappear, and I did it for
super.viewWillDisappear，我还用了
super.viewDidLoad, and super.viewWillAppear.
super.viewDidLoad 和 super.viewWillAppear
All of them, all of the view controller lifecycle methods,
所有这些，所有视图控制器生命周期的方法
always call super.
总是要调用 super
You always wanna give your super class chance to do it.
你总是要给你的父类一个完成它工作的机会
You'll see actually in the demo why you do that.
你将会在我的示范中了解为什么要这么做
Always do that.
但记住总是要这么做
Always do super there.
总要调用这个 super
So in viewWillDisappear, a lot of times here you're
在 viewWillDisappear 里，很多时候你都是在
undoing the things you did in viewDidAppear.
撤销你在 viewDidAppear 所做过的事情
Like if you had an animation going,
比如说如果你在那有个动画效果
you're gonna stop it here,
那么你就要在这把它停下
because you're about to disappear.
因为你就要消失了
Here you might also start some cleanup.
你还可能在这进行一些清理工作
Your MVC disappeared, and
你的 MVC 消失了
so, if you allocated some resources or something that
如果你分配了一些已经不需要的资源或者什么别的东西
you don't need, network connection open or something.
又或是开启的网络链接或者什么其他的东西
That only makes sense to be open while your MVC is on,
总之只有在你的 MVC 运行的时候开启才有用的
then here is a good place where you can shut it down,
那么这里就是一个你关闭它的好地方
and there is a did version of this as well.
它也有一个 did 的版本
A lot of times people look at viewDidAppear and
很多时候我们将 viewDidAppear
viewWillDisappear as matched, you know, one undoes
和 viewWillDisappear 视为一对儿，你懂的，一个撤销
the other, and then the same thing with viewWillAppear and
另外一个做过的事情；viewWillAppear
viewDidDisappear, those are gonna undo each other.
和 viewDidDisappear 也一样，一个撤销另一个做的事
I still haven't talked about geometry until now.
直到现在我们还没有讨论布局相关的事
You don't want to be doing geometry in viewWillAppear.
你不会想在 viewWillAppear 中布局
Your geometry actually probably is set
虽然在 viewWillAppear 被调用时
in viewWillAppear, but you shouldn't count on that.
布局相关的已经不会变了，但是你不应该指望它
You shouldn't do geometry in the view wills and
你也不应该在各种 viewWill
did appears and disappears either.
didAppear 或 disappear 中布局
Geometry changes: there's methods especially for it.
布局，有专门设置它们的方法
One thing to consider is, you almost never need to write any
有一件需要注意的事就是，你几乎不用写任何代码
code when your geometry changes.
来完成需要的重新布局
That's cuz you have auto layout.
那是因为你使用了自动布局（Auto Layout）
I mean, look at the app I just wrote.
我的意思是，你看我刚刚写的这个 app
I've got that sad, happy, worried block of text, and
Sad，Happy 和 Worried 那一块内容
when I rotate it it stays in the middle.
即使在我旋转设备的时候，它们始终在中间
I didn't have to write any code for that.
我不需要为此写任何代码
And even more complicated UI's.
即使在更加复杂的 UI 中
You're usually using auto layout and
你也会经常用自动布局
it's doing it for you.
来帮你做这些工作
So most time you don't need any code.
所以大部分时间你不需要任何代码
But if you did feel like you needed to do some code
但是如果你觉得你还是想写一些代码的话
Let's talk a little bit about how you do that.
我也可以教你一点怎么写
There's two methods, viewWillLayoutSubviews and
这有两个方法，viewWillLayoutSubviews
viewDidLayoutSubviews.
和 viewDidLayoutSubviews
And these are sent to you.
你的这两个方法会被调用
In between these being sent to you, Autolayout happens.
而自动布局是在它们之间发生的
So if you wanna get involved in the geometry change of your
所以如果你想在自动布局发生前
view, before Autolayout starts,
插手改变你的形状和/或位置的话
you can do it in view will layout subviews.
你可以使用 viewWillLayoutSubviews 方法
If you wanna wait until Autolayout does what it does
如果你想等自动布局做完它的工作之后
and then you wanna get involved,
再插手控制的话
you can do it in viewDidLayoutSubviews.
你可以用 viewDidLayoutSubviews 方法
So when did these get called?
所以它们在什么时候会被调用呢？
When a bounds of a view changes,
在视图的边界改变时
all of its subviews might have to be moved around.
可能所有的子视图都会改变他们的位置
Maybe the view is know tall and
视图可能会从又长又细
thin, instead of short and wide.
变成又短又宽
It's views are gonna have to be moved to be in the right
这时它的子视图必须被移动到正确的位置上去
place, just like again we rotated the emotions thing and
就像我们的 Face It，当我们旋转设备时
we need to move that stack view up or
我们需要把那个 UIStackView
all over a little bit sustained in the middle.
整体向上移才能使它保持在中间
That's primarily what's going on here,
差不多就是这样
that's why this method is called viewWillLayoutSubviews.
所以这个方法叫做“视图将要布局子视图”
Its bounds changed and
它的边界改变了
now all its subviews need to be laid out.
然后它的所有子视图都要重新被布局
What about the things the view actually draws itself like
但是那些自己进行绘图的视图要怎么办呢？
the face?
比如 FaceView
That has nothing to do with this.
它们什么都不用在这里做
That's a view thing.
那是视图负责的
That face view, when the bounds change, if it's content
当 FaceView 边界改变时，如果 contentMode
mode is redraw like we set it for the face view, it's draw
内容模式是我们设置的重绘，也就是 .redraw
method's automatically gonna get called at the new bounds.
draw(新的边界) 就会被调用（来重新绘图）
So you don't have to do anything there.
所以你不需要在这里做任何事
So viewWillLayoutSubviews,
所以 viewWillLayoutSubviews
is what happens, when you have subviews.
只有当你有子视图的时候才会发生
This happens at the view level, so views have a method
这是在视图层面发生的；视图有方法
for laying out their subviews, called layoutSubviews.
用 layoutSubviews 布局子视图
And the ViewController also gets to
然后视图控制器也能了解到
find out when its view, and by this I mean the var
它的 view，也就是那个变量
view in ViewController, you remember what that var is?
UIViewController 的 view 变量，你记得那个吧？
That's that top level view.
那个是最顶层的视图
There's a var for that in your ViewController,
UIViewController 里有这么个变量
it's saying that view is going to layout its subviews, and
总之控制器会知道这个 view 将布局子视图了
that happens when that top level view changes, usually
在最顶层的视图改变时就会被通知
due to rotation, but other things can change it as well.
一般都是发生在设备旋转时，但是也有一些其他东西会触发（这种变化）
One thing about these methods is you should expect that they
关于这些方法，有一点需要注意，那就是你应该
may be called all the time.
做好它们会被随时调用的准备
Don't try to anticipate when they're going to be called.
不要尝试去预期它们什么时候会被调用
Just, whenever they're called, you do
不管什么时候它们被调用
what you're supposed to do,
你就做好你该做的工作
and they might be called repeatedly with the same
而且它们可能在相同的边界下被重复的
bounds.
调用
So the bounds might not actually have changed,
所以可能边界并没有被改变
because this is not called view bounds changed this is
因为这个方法并不叫做“视图边界被改变”
called viewWillLayoutSubviews and viewDidLayoutSubviews.
它叫做“视图将要布局子视图”和“视图已经布局好了子视图”
And there are other things besides bounds changes that
所以也有一些除了视图边界被改变的情况
might cause that top-level view to have to layout it's
也可能导致顶级视图不得不布局它的
sub views.
子视图们
So expect this to be called fairly often and
所以做好它们被相当频繁调用的准备
you should always react to it correctly.
你总是应该做出正确的反应
Even if it's called repeatedly with the same
即使它们在同一边界下或其他各种情况下
bounds or whatever.
被频繁调用
Now, auto rotation,
现在我们来讲自动旋转
the bounds changing by rotating the device, actually
边界会因为设备的旋转而改变，实际上
has a couple of little extra pieces of interest to it.
还有两个额外的小东西我们要注意下
The most notable is animation.
最值得注意的就是动画效果
So normally when you rotate it's just going to be
所以一般情况下，当你旋转屏幕时
ViewWillLayoutSubviews and everything's just going to,
viewWillLayoutSubviews 会发生
auto layout's going to happen, everything is happening fine.
自动布局会发生，所有的事都进行的很好
However that changes, all those changes are animated.
不管它怎么变，所有这些变化都伴随着动画效果
If you look closely when you rotate your device, all
如果你在旋转屏幕时仔细观察你会发现
the views are kind of flying across to their new location.
所有的视图都像是飞到它们的新位置一样
It's really kinda cool actually.
这样看起来可以说非常酷了
They're being animated.
它们都伴随有动画效果
They don't just pop appear in the new place,
它们并不是突然出现在新位置上
they slide over.
它们滑过去
Well, you can participate in that animation,
当然你也可以插手设置这些动画效果
now we haven't talked about animation.
到现在我们还没有讨论过动画效果
We will in about three weeks.
我们大概三周之内会讨论它
But you can participate with this method,
但是你可以用这个方法参与这个过程
ViewwillTransition to size with coordinator.
用 viewwillTransition(to size:with coordinator:)
And that coordinator has a little closure you can set on
负责协调的 coordinator 有个闭包可以设置
it that will cause some animation you want to do
来做一些你想要的动画效果
to happen alongside the rotations animation.
一些你想在设备旋转时发生的动画效果
So if you want to animate moving some user doing
所以如果你想对一些用户的移动操作加上动画效果
something else that doesn't happen automatically for you,
加上一些并没有被自动设置出现的动画效果
which most stuff does with autolayout,
就是那些没有使用自动布局的东西
you can do that here with this method.
你可以在这里用这个方法实现
Low-memory: didReceiveMemoryWarning
低内存：didReceiveMemoryWarning
will be sent to your view controller when
将在你的系统内存不足时
the system's low on memory, it's trying to get some back.
发送给你的视图控制器，它想搞一些回来
This almost never happens.
这种情况基本从不发生
I just can't remember the last time this happened because
我都不记得上次遇到这种情况是什么时候了
the devices have so much memory these days.
因为现在的设备内存都很大
Usually if this happens though, you wanna pay
但是通常如果发生了这样的事情，你需要
attention because you're using a lot of memory.
注意了，因为你正在使用大量的内存
If the system is sending this to you, either you are or
如果系统发送这个信息给你了，要么是你
some other app is using a lot of memory.
要么是其他 app 正在使用大量的内存
By the way, if you are an app that uses a lot of memory, and
如果你的 app 正在使用大量的内存
you don't keep it under control,
而你又不加以控制
the system has the right to just kill you.
那么系统就有权利杀掉你的程序
Just kill your app.
杀掉你的 app
And it will do it, absolutely.
它是一定会这么做的
Even if you're in the background,
即使你在后台运行
if you've allocated a ton of memory and you're being a bad
如果你分配了一大吨内存，而你又不控制
citizen they just kill you off to get your memory back what
那么系统就会杀掉你的进程，然后把内存拿回来
kinda memory would you free up if you got this method.
如果你遇到了这个方法，什么样的内存你可以释放呢？
Let's say you had an image that's not currently on
我们说如果你有个图片，这个图片现在还不会出现在屏幕上
screen, and you can create it from a file on disk.
然后你可以通过磁盘上的文件来创建它
We haven't really talked about this, but your phone has
我们还没确切的讨论过这些，但是你的手机是有
permanent storage, flash memory, and you have,
永久存储和闪存的
let's say a JPEG image, you can just recreate it.
比如一个 JPEG 格式的图片，你完全可以重建它
Well, you would definitely release that here.
那么这样的话，你就完全可以把它释放掉
Cuz it's not on-screen, and
因为它现在不在屏幕上
you can create it real fast from the disk,
而且你可以非常迅速地通过磁盘上的文件来创建它
so there's no reason to keep it around.
这样的话，把它留在那里就完全没有必要了
So that's something you could release.
这就是一些你可以释放的东西
Basically any memory that you can quickly recreate.
基本上任何你可以快速重建的
Or that is not currently on-screen, and
或者它现在不在屏幕上的
you can create it when that comes back on-screen.
你可以在它会到屏幕上之前再创建
That's a good thing to release.
都是可以释放的内存
But only big things.
但是只释放大的东西
Don't release little tiny 100 byte things.
不要释放那些小的只有几百字节的东西
No, we're talking images, sounds, videos,
我们说的都是一些图片啊音频啊视频之类的东西
big ol' things.
大～东西
There's one other little thing:
这还有个小事情要说
it's not part of the view controller life cycle, but
它并不是视图控制器生命周期的一部分
every single object that comes out of a storyboard: views,
但是每一个 Storyboard 创建的对象
view controllers, everything gets sent awakeFromNib and
比如视图和视图控制器，所有的都会被调用 awakeFromNib
they can send it pretty early.
它们可以非常早的接收到它
Like right as soon as they come
就像它们一出现
out they get sent awake from nib.
就收到了这个 awakeFromNib
Now you can't use it to like satisfy the requirement that
虽然说你不能在这里满足
all vars are initialized.
所有的变量都初始化的要求
But you can use it do early, really early initialization.
但是你可以使用它完成非常早的初始化工作
For example remember I mentioned about you want your
举个例子，我记得我提过关于你如果想要你的
split view controller to come up showing the face or
分屏视图控制器先出现表情选择列表
come up showing the emotions instead of showing the face?
而不是先出现一张脸
In your calculator,
在你的计算器里
it would come up showing the calculator,
它应该先出现计算器界面
instead of the calculator's graph, and
而不是出现计算的图像
I said you needed to do that by setting the delegate.
然后我说如果想设置这个的话需要设置代理
This delegate of the SplitViewController,
UISplitViewController 的代理
that's something you might wanna do to make awakeFromNib
这个可以在 awakeFromNib 中设置
Just really early, get that delegate involved early.
来让代理更早地起作用
We'll talk about delegates on Wednesday.
我们将在周三讲代理
So awake from nib, rarely used and sometimes overused.
所以这个 awakeFromNib，要么基本不用要么过度使用
I would say if you could put it in another method like view
我会这么告诉你们，如果你能把它放在其他方法里，比如
did load or view will appear or view.
viewDidLoad 或者 viewWillAppear 或者
Did layout put it there first.
viewDidLayout，那么就优先把它放在那里
Don't put it in away fromNib,
不要把它放在 awakeFromNib 里
that's kind of a last resort place to put things.
它就是一个你可以放它的最差的一个地方
It's probably better than overriding init.
可能比重写构造器好
But that's the only thing it's better than.
但是也就能比重写构造器好些了
So here's the summary of the entire view controller
这是整个视图控制器
lifecycle.
生命周期的总结
You can instantiated, created out of the storyboard.
你被实例化，从 Stroyboard 中创建
You get awake from nib sent to you.
你会收到一个 awakeFromNib
Segue prep happens.
完成 Segue 前的准备
Somebody prepares you if you're being segued to
转场到你之前，其他人会把你准备好
which most MVC's are.
大部分 MVC 都会这么做
Outlets get set.
出口也都设置好了
Your face view, and your calculator.
想你的 FaceView 还有你的 Calculator
It's your display and things like that get set up.
你的 display 和其他要关连都设置好了
ViewDidLoad gets called.
viewDidLoad 被调用
Again, with viewDidLoad, look at all the things that
再一次，看看 viewDidLoad 被调用时
happened by the time viewDidLoad gets called.
这些事都发生了
It's a great place to put initialization.
这是个非常好进行初始化的地方
You enter kind of the normal life cycle
当你进入到一个常规的生命周期
where you're getting appearing and disappearing.
在这里你进行“出现”和“消失”操作
Appearing and disappearing with the the will and did,
disappear 和 appear 都有 will 和 did 的
appears and disappears.
不断出现消失
Along the way, and at any time actually,
在整个过程中的任何时间
even before viewDidLoad, you can get these sent to.
甚至在 viewDidLoad 之前，你都可能收到它们
Although that would be rare.
虽然这种情况很罕见
But anytime you can be,
但是也是可能发生的
actually I'm not sure you can get it before viewDidLoad.
事实上我不是特别确定你会不会在 viewDidLoad 之前收到它，先收回那句话
Take that back But any time when view will appear and
但是任何时间 viewWillAppear 和 Disappear发生了
disappear is happening, whether you're on-screen or
不管你是否出现在屏幕上
not, you could get viewWillLayout subviews and
你都会得到 viewWillLayoutSubviews 和
viewDidLayout subviews sent to you, auto-layout happening.
viewDidLayoutSubviews 的信息，自动布局会发生
By the way, why would you ever be sent these methods
那么你为什么会在不在屏幕上的情况下
when you're not on-screen?
接收到这些方法呢？
Well, the system might be preparing to animate you
可能是因为系统正在准备
coming on-screen.
你即将出现在屏幕上的动画效果
When the system animates things,
当系统在进行一些动画效果的时候
one of the ways it can do it is having you draw one
一种它实现的方法是，获取你在一个方向的画面
orientation, have you draw in the other, and
再获取你在另一个方向画的
then it kind of moves the bits from one to the other.
然后它就把对应的点移动到另外一个
That's one kind of animation can do.
这是生成动画效果的一种方式
So you might be off screen, and it's asking you for
所以这样的话，你可能不在屏幕上，但是它依然会从你这里获取
both of those.
这两个东西
So it sends you this twice,
所以它会发送给你两次
once to get this orientation and draw, and
第一次获得一个方向下绘制的内容
then once to get this into orientation and draw.
然后第二次获得另一个方向的内容
And then when you come on screen,
然后等你在屏幕上时
it animate you from one to the other.
它就会动态地把你从一个移到另一个
So, that's why you can get this at any time
所以这就是为什么你随时都可能得到这个方法
on screen or off.
无论在不在屏幕上
Also at any time you could get a low memory warning.
同时你也可能在任何时间得到低内存警告
And then you're done.
到这就完事了
It leaves the heap when it goes off screen if it was
被 segue 到的控制器就会在离开屏幕的同时离开堆
segued to, as long as it's not itself segued into something.
注意不是它 segue 到了另一个控制器
But when it's done it gets thrown out.
如果是被 segue 到的，那就被扔出去了
Okay, so I'm gonna show you a demo that
现在我要向大家展示一个示例程序
will make all of this a lot more concrete.
这样可以使我们讲的所有的东西都更具体
Let me go through the rest of this in case I don't get
我们过一下剩下的这些，万一我不能
back to the slides, I think we will, because
回来讲幻灯片的话，我觉得我们还是会回来的
I think we're gonna have time to do this other, topic.
因为我觉得我演示完之后还会有些时间来讲另一个主题
After the demo, I'll come back and
我会回到这里然后
start to talk about memory management, hopefully.
开始讨论一些内存管理，希望如此吧
On Wednesday, extensions, protocols, delegation,
周三，我们会讲扩展（extension）、协议（protocol）和代理（delegation）
that thing I was telling you you'll need to know for
代理可以用来完成
your split view thing, if you wanna do that extra credit.
分屏视图控制器的加分题
And we'll start talking about scroll view,
然后我们会开始讨论滚动视图
more complicated object.
更复杂的对象
On Friday, important one on Friday,
周五，周五很重要
if you want to do the extra credit,
如果你想在你的图形计算器的性能上
about performance in the calculator graph.
获得额外的分数
So you definitely wanna show up for that one.
那你一定要去那天的课
And then next week we'll start into multi threading,
然后下周我们会开始讨论多线程
table view, a whole bunch of cool stuff.
UITableView，一连串酷酷的东西
Alright, so let's do this demo here.
那么现在我们来做这个 demo 吧
I'm gonna go to our face view, same thing we were just in,
我要用我们的 FaceView 来做，我们刚刚用过的这个东西
this face it app.
就是这个 FaceIt app
And I'm gonna drag in a little piece of code I wrote,
然后我要拖进来一小块我写的代码
which I'm gonna show you here.
我要在这里展示给你
Let's get out navigator back here, put this in here.
我们把导航器拉出来，把它放这
So I'm just gonna drop this in here.
我就把它丢在这里
By the way when you drag in code,
顺便一提，当你拖拽代码时
you probably want to do copy items, if needed.
你可能会想用这个 Copy items if needed
Otherwise, it's gonna be kind of linked to the other one,
要不然它只会是快捷方式
if you change it in the other place,
如果你在其他地方对它做了些改动
it's gonna be changing here.
那么这里的也会相应变化
Can be kinda causing unexpected results often.
这样的话可能经常会导致很多预期之外的后果
I put this in here.
我把这个放这
Let's look at this little class I just dropped in here,
我们来看看我刚刚丢在这里的这个小类
it's called VCLLoggingViewController.
它叫做 VCLLoggingViewController
It's a subclass of UIViewController.
他是 UIViewController 的一个子类
VCLLoggingViewController. And it logs the VCL methods.
它会记录 VCL 的方法
View controller life cycle methods.
视图控制器（VC）生命周期(L)方法
So it basically just overrides every single one.
所以它基本上就是重写了每一个方法
View will appear, view layout subviews, awake from nib.
viewWillAppear, viewWillLayoutSubviews, awakeFromNib
It even tells you when it left the heap.
它甚至可以告诉你它什么时候离开堆
It's overriding init here, and
它在这重写了一个构造器
it just prints out what happened.
它就是把发生了什么打印出来
So it just sits there on the console,
它就在控制台那里
printing out everything that happened.
打印所有发生的事情
It's a little bit cool,
还是挺酷的
because it shows you the instance of each of them.
因为它会告诉你它们的每个实例都发生了什么
So you can see instances coming and going,
所以你可以看到实例们出现然后消失
as they get segued to, and then come off.
被 segue 到，然后又离去
It also kinda indents it over time, so you can, when you
每当过去一段时间，它会增加缩进
click some, you can see a bunch that happen together.
你进行操作的时候，可以看到一连串发生的事情
Now the way we're gonna use this is we're just gonna make
我们使用它的方式就是
this class be the super class of both of our controllers.
把它变成我们两个控制器的父类
So we're gonna make that into a VCL login view controller.
也就是把它们变成 VCLLoggingViewController
And we're gonna make this into a VCL login view controller.
把这个 UIViewController 改成 VCLLoggingViewController
And right there, you can see why we always wanna call super
然后这里，你就明白为什么在所有视图控制器方法中
in all of our view control methods.
我们总是要调用 super 了
Cuz if we did any of these view controller
如果任何一个控制器生命周期
life cycle methods, and
的方法被调用了
we were subclassing from VCL login view controller,
同时我们继承了 VCLLoggingViewController
if we don't call super, it not gonna get logged.
但我们不调用 super，那么就不会被记录
And it's not unusual to come along later and
这并不罕见，随时可能
pop the different kind of view controller in between you and
在你和 UIViewController 之间
UI view controller.
插入一个其他的类
Some view controller that does something like logging or
比如用来记录的视图控制器
something else.
或者其他的什么
All right, so that's it.
好啦 就是这样
That's all we need to do to make this work.
这就是我们为了让它工作所做的所有的事情
So I'm gonna go ahead and
所以我要继续了
run, we'll stick with iPhone 7 plus.
我们在 iPhone 7 Plus 上运行
Let's go ahead and get the console up here.
我们来看看，把这个控制台往上拉
Here we go.
来吧
This came up, and we're already seeing a lot of
它们出现了，我们已经看到了很多
view controller lifecycle stuff happening here.
视图控制器生命周期的东西出现了
All right, we have our EmotionsViewController and
我们这里有我们的 EmotionsViewController 和
our FaceViewController,
我们的 FaceViewController
these two view controllers get emitted.
这两个视图控制器出现了
They come out of the storyboard, and
它们从 Storyboard 中被初始化
they initialize with this init with coder.
它们通过这个 init(coder:) 来初始化
And that's the one that is for things
这个构造器是给
come out the interface builder.
Interface Builder 中的东西用的
They both get awakeFromNib, you see that?
它们都被调用了 awakeFromNib，你看见了么？
And then the emotions one, first, gets viewDidLoad.
EmotionViewController 先获得 viewDidLoad
Then it gets viewwillAppear(animated = false)
然后它有个 viewwillAppear(animated = false）
That's because we're
这是因为
just starting up our app,
我们才开始运行我们的 app
so it's not sliding in on a navigation controller or something.
并不是滑入一个导航控制器或者别的什么东西
It's just appearing, so it's not animated.
它就简单的出现了，所以并没有动画效果
Then notice, it gets laid out twice, both at the same size,
这里注意，它布局了两次，都在相同的尺寸下
295 x 414, which is this size right here.
295 x 414，就是现在这个尺寸
It gets look, done twice.
它做了两次
Again, Why?
所以到底是为什么呢？
Some animation, I don't know wha's going on,
可能是一些动画效果？我并不知道
why i's doing that.
它为什么这么做
But you don't care,
但是你不必在意
just be careful that those layouts can happen repeatedly.
只要注意，这些布局可能频繁的发生
Now here is face view controller, it gets loaded.
现在这是个 FaceViewController，他已经被加载好了
It's told it's going to appear, it will appear.
它被告知将要出现了，willAppear
And it gets laid out once.
而且它被布局了一次
Then they both get DidAppear, and now they're on screen.
然后它们现在都有了 didAppear，然后它们现在都在屏幕上了
So this is kind of exactly what you'd expect.
这完全就是如我们所预想的
Now let's rotate this thing, so
现在我们来旋转一下设备
that we go to portrait mode.
这样我们就来到了纵向模式
And we're not gonna see the master.
然后我们就看不见主视图了
We're only gonna see the details here.
我们只能看见这里的细节
So here, the master disappears.
所以这里，主视图消失了
So this is, see the dash?
看见这些下划线了么？
That's what happened when I did that rotation.
这就是在我旋转设备的时候发生了什么
So this is all the new stuff.
所以这些都是新的东西
Now notice that the EmotionViewController
现在注意力放在 EmotionViewController 上
immediately is
它立即被
told that there's going to be a rotation animation.
告知，这里即将出现一个旋转设备相关的动画效果
And it gets a chance to participate in the animation.
然后它就有了参与这个动画效果的机会
The FaceView gets re-laid out in its new size.
这个 FaceView 在它的新尺寸下被重新布局了
It's tall now, so it gets laid out, so
它现在高了，所以它被布局好了
it gets viewWillLayoutSubviews.
它获得了 viewWillLayoutSubviews
The Emotions Controller is told that it will disappear.
EmotionsViewController 被告知它要消失了
So it's going to disappear.
所以它就要消失了
Notice the animated = false, that's cuz the animation in
注意这个 animated = false，这是因为旋转时的动画
that rotation case is handled by the rotation animation.
是交给旋转动画效果处理的
So it's not sliding in or out but it is getting animated
所以它并不是滑入滑出，他的动画效果
out of there but by the rotation animation.
是由旋转动画效果来呈现的
Then we have
然后我们的
the face view controller being laid out again.
FaceViewController 又被重新布局了
Now we're getting the EmotionsViewControllers
现在 EmotionsViewController
being getting it's chance to
获得了机会参与设置
animate alongside the rotation, right here.
旋转时的动画效果了，就这里
We've got a couple of spurious things here from
这里是 iOS UIKit 的胡言乱语
the iOS new UIKit, we can get rid of those.
我们完全不用管它们
And then the animation ends for both of those controllers.
然后两个控制器的动画效果结束了
Make sense?
说得通吧？
Now I'm gonna click this emotions thing, and
现在我要来点击一下这个 Emotions
go back to the master and watch what happens.
然后回到主视图看看会发生什么
Okay, so we go back to the master.
FaceViewController was told it would disappear,
of course, cuz it did, does disappear.
The emotions one is told that it will appear,
it's laid out in this new tall arrangement.
And then the face view controller told it,
was disappeared and
the emotion view controller was told it disappeared.
Now let's go, bring one back.
You can see, look, FaceViewController(2).
A new FaceViewController was created,
because we segued to it, so it created it.
You see that?
And in fact, if we go back and forth, we'll see that we're
getting new FaceViewControllers each time,
FaceView three.
And look at the old one's, FaceViewController
3 left heap, they're gonna thrown out beneath.
So I'll be posting all this code.
You can drop this logging view controller.
Actually you can drop it into your calculator,
if you wanted, and try and watch it bring things on and
off screen etc.
Let's go back to the slides here.
Let's talk about our next topic,
which is memory management.
We've kind of avoided this topic so far but
i's an important topping topic.
If you have a reference counted data structure,
a class tha's the only reference,
well i's not the only data counting reference structure
as you'll see in a second.
But if you have a reference counting thing, and it lives
in the heap, how do you know when to get rid of it?
We saw in that demo I just did the faceview controller
left the heap.
How did it know to leave the heap?
Because we don't do anything to tell it to leave the heap.
We just are using it, and
when we're not using it anymore it goes away.
Well, of course, you know one way to make things leave
the heap, it's called garbage collection.
How many people know what garbage collection is,
have heard that phrase before?
So, more than half of you, so that's good.
Runtimes like Java, do garbage collection.
It's a perfectly fine way to do it.
It involves going through the heap and
kind of marking the use of everything and
then sweeping through and
getting rid of stuff that's not used.
Swift doesn't do any of that, it uses a totally different
mechanism called Automatic Reference Counting.
Basically every time you create a var or
a let that points to something in a heap,
Swift goes over somewhere and makes a mark.
And another one, there's another one.
And it keeps track of it until there aren't anymore of those
lets and vars.
It erases them as those vars go away.
Like, maybe they're
a var in another object that leaves the heap.
So now that var is no longer pointing to this other object.
So it's basically keeping track of all the vars unless
they point to something in the heap.
And when no one points to any more,
it lets it out of the heap.
Now why is this good?
It's very predictable memory usage.
You know exactly when things are gonna leave the heap.
They leave the heap as soon as nobody points to them anymore.
What's also great about it, is that you almost have to
do nothing in your code to make this work.
It's just automatic.
That's why it's called automatic reference counting.
You can get involved however.
And the way you can get involved is by influencing
the way that arc works.
And you do that with three keywords in Swift
called strong, weak and unowned.
And I actually told you and I was gonna tell you about these
back in the very first lecture, you remember when we
made the outlet for display, it was weak.
Remember that?
That's this weak right here.
So the strong, weak and unknown.
So let's talk about each of those.
Strong, this is normal reference counting.
If you have a strong var or
strong let to something in the heap, then that thing
will stay in the heap, as long as that var exists,
it's strongly holding that thing in the heap.
This is the default.
You don't even ever type this keyword, cuz it's the default.
Every var, unless you say it's weak, is going to be strong.
So it's simple.
Works magically.
Then there's weak.
Now weak is a really interesting keyword in Swift.
When you put weak on top of a var,
it says, well I'm looking at this thing in the heap but
if no one else is interested in the heap then
you can throw it out of the heap and set me to nil.
So weak only works with what type?
>> Optional. >> Optional, exactly,
cuz you have to be able to set it to nil.
So only optionals can be weak.
So the display outlet in your calculator,
it was a weak UI label exclamation point,
which means it was an optional UI label.
And so it was weak.
So what does that mean?
That means if that UI label for
some reason ever, everyone else threw it out,
then that display var would be set to nil, automatically.
Now, why does that display var set itself weak?
Why does it say weak?
Well, because the thing it's pointing to is that view
hierarchy.
The view hierarchy that has all the calculator buttons and
the display and all in there.
And if that view hierarchy stops pointing to it,
that means it's gone, and so the display outlet is no
longer interested in trying to set numbers in it, and
things like that, because it's gone.
So, when you have a var that points into a very strongly
held data structure that you completely depend on for
your semantic meaning to mean anything
then you can make it weak.
And so we're perfectly fine if that display gets at the nil
if the view hierarchy no longer points to that UI label
because it's probably meaningless at that point.
So we don't usually use weak that much.
A lot of times we'll use it to keep from having
one object pointing to another strongly and
having that object point back to this one strongly.
That's very bad situation.
That's called a memory cycle.
That's gonna keep both of those objects in the heap
forever, because there's always gonna be a strong
pointer to each of them.
Cuz they each point to each other.
So either of them can leave the heap and
free up their pointer to the other one.
Unless you set one,
like they're optionally set one to nil or something.
So if you had a situation like that,
you could use weak to break that cycle by having one
of the pointers be a weak pointer.
That would allow it possibly to happen.
And I'm gonna show you an example here of another
case where making that kind of memory cycle is super easy.
And that's bad that it's easy.
Because you can get the cycles where things are being
held in memory.
The last one is unowned.
Unowned means, "Hey, automatic reference counter, Don't worry
about this one, I'll take care of it, I'll make sure I never
use it when it's not pointing to something in the heap".
This one can be quite dangerous.
We almost never use this.
It would really only be used to break one of these memory
cycles, and it can only be used to make a memory cycle
when you're 100% sure that you know who's
using that pointer, because automatic reference counting
is not going to be counting it as a strong reference, and
it's also not going to check.
And so if you use it, and that thing you're pointing to
has left the heap, it will crash your program.
So that's what unowned is.
Now, since unowned just crashes your program if you
try to use it and it's not in the heap,
it's not an optional.
There is no setting to nil,
it's always assumed to not be nil.
And if it's ever nil and
that code executes, bam, it crashes.
So unowned,
I will show you how we use unowned in a moment.
It's only to break cycles.
Now, closures have an interesting attribute
about them, which hopefully you read about in your reading
assignment, that really has a lot to do with this strong,
weak, and unowned business.
And then what goes on inside of a closure is that a closure
captures all the references inside of it.
It captures them, and makes a strong pointer to them.
So, if you reference something inside a closure,
remember what closures are.
Open curly braces, and
we have some code in there like we had in our
operations table of our calculator brain.
So inside that closure,
inside those curly braces you reference some reference type,
something that's in the heap.
That closure is itself a reference type.
It lives in the heap and
it's going to keep a strong pointer to the other thing.
And the problem comes if that other thing has a strong
pointer back to that closure.
Because now you have a memory cycle.
The closure is keeping that object in and that object that
has a pointer to the closure is keeping the closure in.
They are keeping each other in memory.
Now neither of them can ever leave.
It's called a memory cycle and it's really easier memory
cycle in a closure, as you'll see.
So, here is an example with our calculator.
Let's say I added a new method to my calculator brain called
addUnaryOperation where I allow people to
add new operations to my operations table.
Right now we don't allow that because it's all private.
But let's say I had a public method, addUnaryOperation.
You could add a new operation.
Wouldn't that be cool?
Yeah, that would be cool.
Let's see what it would like for
a view controller that wanted to, for
example, add a unary operation which is square root, but
it turns the display green.
I call it green square root.
So, what will it look like to write something like that?
Well, I would call addUnaryOperation,
give it some symbol.
I'm gonna have it look like a green square root but
it's pushing it there but it's kind of what it looks like.
And it would pass in the operation for
green square root.
Now just a couple of cleanup things before that here.
This is that operation argument to addUnary
operation.
And as we know, we could use trailing
closure syntax here to get rid of that operation colon.
We just close it, and since the closure is the last
argument, we just put it after the end of the parenthesis.
Remember that from when I talked about filter and map?
So we could do that here, so that cleans it up.
Also, of course,
we could let Swift infer the types here and just use $0.
Everyone understand this code up here?
Could not be simpler, right?
I'm just adding this Unary operation, green square root.
And all it's doing is setting, this, I'm doing this from
my view controller, so it's setting the displays color to
green And returning square roots,
the same as square root, but the display is just green.
Now, this will not compile.
Why will this not compile?
Let us look and see why not.
It's because it's gonna say you have to explicitly say
self dot there because I want you to understand that you
are capturing a strong pointer to yourself In this closure.
So that in case somehow you point to this closure,
which our view controller does,
because our view controller has the calculator brain,
calculator brain has the operations table,
the operations table has this closure in it.
So I'm pointing to that indirectly
from my View Controller, and it's pointing now back at me.
Self dot, it's gonna capture self.
Self is a pointer to myself, my own View Controller.
Now I've created a memory cycle.
Yep.
Everyone understand what's going on there?
The closure lives in the heap.
The View Controller lives in the heap.
They're now pointing to each other.
The closure's pointing directly to the view
controller and the view controller's indirectly
pointing to the closure through the calculator brain,
through the operations table.
This operation they've gotta add in.
So let's talk about how we break this cycle
because since it's so
easy to do we need to be able to break it easily as well.
Well first thing we're going to do,
is we're going to create a special local variable.
So closures allow you to before the word in,
put open square bracket, a list of special variables.
These are just little local variables that just live for
this closure only.
Now these variables can have any name.
And you can set them to any value you want that's in
the scope here.
So I've created a local variable called me and
I've set it equal to self.
So that's fine, "me" is a local variable,
it's going to be of type view controller,
it's added to myself and so now I can use me in there and
you already used self so I've replaced self with me.
That doesn't help break our cycle at all.
However, what if I made that me variable,
not self but me, be unowned?
If I make that thing be unowned,
now it's not going to create that strong pointer.
Because me It lives in the heap, but
automatic reference counting doesn't reference count it, so
it pays no attention to it.
Now what that would mean though,
is that if this code were executed, and me,
which is the view controller cuz I set it equal to self, if
the view controller were out of the heap, this would crash.
But that's perfectly fine here.
Do you see why that's fine?
When would a calculator operation ever be executed
if the view controller is not even in the heap?
It's impossible.
The view controller provides all the UI that causes this
thing to be executed.
There's absolutely no way that can happen, so
it's perfectly fine to say unowned here.
And that would break the cycle nicely.
But let's talk about another way to do it.
By the way, it doesn't have to be called 'me',
I could say 'unknown self' equals 'self'.
In other words, the local variable can shadow or
have the same name as the more global variable 'self'.
So I could say unknown self equals self, and
in fact if I just say unknown self that's the same as
saying 'unknown self equals self.
So this is a lot of times how we'll break a cycle,
we'll say unknown self and that basically means inside
this enclosure, you can assume that self is in the heap.
Now let's talk about breaking it with weak.
So I can also say weak self.
And that means that self is now a local variable in this
closure that's an optional view controller.
And if it's not, if that view controller is not in the heap,
this variable self, which is different from the global cell
is going to be nil.
So this is a safe way to do it.
But of course since it's an optional,
we can't just say self.display,
right there we have to say optional chained self.display.
So that if this closure executes and
the view controller is not in the heap, self question mark
will be nil and it will not execute the rest of that line.
It'll still return the square root,
but it won't turn the thing green because
this view controller's not even there.
So that's how we can use weak to do it.
And sometimes we use weak, and we could create anther
variable, and often we'll do this.
This might be the most common way to do it right here,
is to say weak weakself equals self.
And so, weakself is this Argument,
is this local variable inside the closure only
that is a weak version of Self.
Okay, that's kind of clearer
what's going on than if you just say weakSelf.
Then it's like self is an optional, it's weird.
Now at least you have a different variable called
weakSelf, all right.
Okay, so let's go in the last couple minutes and
just do this in the Calculator.
Let's do exactly what I talked about, this green square root.
I'm just gonna go back to our calculator here.
Where is our calculator?
Here somewhere.
There it is.
We haven't seen this code in a while.
You've seen it a lot.
I haven't seen it in a long time.
All right, so here's our calculator, and
I told you I'm just going to add this new func.
Add unary operation.
And it's going to take the symbol that we
want to have it be this in there, so it's gonna be like
the green square root, or whatever we call it there.
And actually, probably we wanna say something like named
symbol, that's probably be a little better naming there,
and that's a string.
And it's going to take an argument,
let's make more space here, which is the operation.
We don't really need to have an external name because we're
probably gonna use trailing closure syntax there to do it.
But this is just a Double, returns a Double function.
Hopefully, you're all very familiar by now with using
a function just as a type right there.
So we have this UnaryOperation.
And all we need to do to make this work is
we have our operations table down here.
I'm just gonna say operations sub that symbol =
Operation.unary operation,
where this operation is the argument.
I mean, it couldn't be simpler.
Really, that was so simple because we built such a good
data structure here to store all of our operations.
Now notice we have an error here.
You see this has an error.
What's it saying?
Mark this method mutating.
Okay, why is that?
Well that's because we're changing this operations table
so of course that has to be mutating.
But that's not the only error, we've got another error.
What's this saying?
It's saying here that this parameter operation
Is "escaping".
What that does that mean, it's escaping?
Let's go ahead and fix it.
It puts this word in here, @escaping.
Escaping means that this function,
is escaping these curly braces.
It is in fact escaping.
Where is it escaping?
It's jumping into here.
Anytime you have a function that you pass in, and
it gets put in some other data structure, in other words,
it escapes out of the curly braces of the method it's in,
you have to mark it escaping so that you understand and
swift understands that you are storing that somewhere.
And that's because it might create a memory cycle
if you do that.
So fix it will automatically remind you about this so
you don't have to remember that so much.
We've got this nice cool new feature and
let's go to our view controller and add it.
Hey how about we use view did load.
Here's view did load, super dot view did load.
I never want to forget that.
So that's going to happen we're all initialized,
our outlets are set.
Let's just go ahead and call that addUnaryOperation here.
Let's call it brain addUnaryOperation.
Is that what I called it?
addUnaryOperation, I don't know why that's not,
there it did it.
It's just a little slow.
addUnaryOperation takes the symbol which is named.
And I'm gonna go ahead and
do that green exclamation point if I can find it here.
Where is that thing?
It's probably pictograph, maybe, no.
Anyone know where that would be?
Let's try, what's it called, checkmark or something.
There it is.
There's our nice symbol right there.
And let's go and add that to our UI as well.
Let's go over here to our story board,
we'll add it instead of Pi.
So, we'll get rid of Pi instead we'll put that
operation in there.
What was it called again?
Check.
Oops, two of them.
We've got this new green square root.
We still have the old square root as well.
But we have to add this operation and
I'm gonna use that trailing closure syntax right there.
And of course we know this is, it's a double takes a double.
And this would be where the stuff goes in there.
But we can let Swift infer this, and just use $0,
square root of $0.
So we've done everything except for the green.
Does everyone agree with this?
I'm adding the unary Operation named this symbol and here is
the second argument put on the trailing closure there.
So how do we turn it green?
Well, we just say display.textColor.
Turns out UILabel has a text color = UIColor.green.
Now, when we put this in here like this,
it's gonna complain.
Why?
Because, reference to property display and
closure requires an explicit self dot
to make the capture semantics explicit.
This is Swift saying watch out.
If you do this, you're going to capture self right here.
And that is going to create a memory cycle.
This closure right here,
which lives in the heap, is pointing to self.
This addUnary operation is going to cause it,
this closure, to be put in the operations table which is
pointed to by the View Controller.
Now they point at each other.
Let's see, what else did I forget here.
Missing return.
Yes.
Return square root.
Everybody cool with that?
Now, to break that cycle, we could say, unowned self in.
That's one way to break the cycle.
We could say, weakSelf = self, if we do this
one though we're gonna have to go here and say weakSelf?
Either of those will break this cycle.
In your homework, I've updated your homework to say you
cannot have any of these cycles in your homework.
Okay, in assignment three.
It's in the evaluation criteria down there.
So I put, posted it on the forum for that too.
So let's go see if this works.
By the way, what happens if we don't break that cycle,
view controllers will just start accumulating in memory.
Because they'll be keeping,
these closures will be keeping them on our memory.
If you, for example, had a CalculatorViewController
that was being pushed on to you know segue two and
then segue away from, it would not go into out of the heap,
it would stay in heap in that case.
Right here is our calculator.
So 81 square root is 9 green square root?
Woo hoo.
Square root and turned to green.
Okay, that's it, see you next time.
If you guys have any questions, I'm here as always.
>> For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.
>> 更多课程详见 stanford.edu